<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The history of the birth, travels, strange adventures, and death of Fortunatus wherein is contained such variety both of comical and tragical discourse, that the like is not afforded in any histories of this nature : there being added likewise several new additions which was not in the original copy from whence it was translated ... : with the illustration of several new pictures.</title>
            <title>Fortunatus (Romance). English.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 206 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 50 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A43915</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2145</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R4743</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12137869</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12137869</idno>
            <idno type="VID">54800</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A43915)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 54800)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 106:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The history of the birth, travels, strange adventures, and death of Fortunatus wherein is contained such variety both of comical and tragical discourse, that the like is not afforded in any histories of this nature : there being added likewise several new additions which was not in the original copy from whence it was translated ... : with the illustration of several new pictures.</title>
                  <title>Fortunatus (Romance). English.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 94 p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by and for T. Haly ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Translation of: Fortunatus (Romance).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:54800:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:54800:1"/>
            <p>THE HISTORY OF THE <hi>Birth, Travels, Strange Adventures,</hi> and <hi>DEATH</hi> of Fortunatus: Wherein is Contained ſuch Variety BOTH OF <hi>COMICAL</hi> AND <hi>Tragical Diſcourſe,</hi> That the like is not afforded in any <hi>Hiſtories</hi> of this Nature.</p>
            <p>There being added likewiſe ſeveral new Additions which was not in the Original Copy from whence it was Tranſlated.</p>
            <p>It being not onely <hi>Uſeful,</hi> but very <hi>Neceſſary</hi> for Old and Young; Wherein they may plainly ſee the Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies of Riches and greatneſs, and learn how to avoid tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptations of that nature, that often brings Men into danger of life. As alſo, Youths may by this be inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted how to behave themſelves in their <hi>Travels,</hi> or upon any occaſion whatſoever.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>With the Illuſtration of ſeveral New Pictures.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by, and for, <hi>T. Haly,</hi> and are to be Sold by the Book-ſellers of <hi>London.</hi> 1682.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:54800:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:54800:2"/>
            <head>THE EPISTLE TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Need not ſay much in the praiſe of this Book, but rather leave it to the cenſure of the impartial Reader, who I doubt not will find ſuch pleaſure in peruſing it, that he will never think his time ill beſtowed upon that occaſion; for in it, as in a mirror, is plainly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrated all the follies of extravagant Youth, the vanity of aſpiring greatneſs, the trouble, perplexity and hazards, that commonly attend upon Riches; as likewiſe the malice, ſubtilty and cunning devices of wicked men; together with the ſnares that are layed by falſe and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembling Women to intrap the too too credulous Youths, and then to plunge them into an Ocean of miſery, which many times drives them upon the dangerous Rock of diſpair, or cauſes them to take bad courſes to maintain that pride and gallantry from whence they are fallen, which in the end moſt commonly brings them to ſhame and diſgrace: In it are likewiſe contained many cautions how to avoid danger, and to fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee the ſame. It being compoſed of large experience, partly Commical and partly Tragical: giving not only an account of the Life, ſtrange Adventures, and Death of the party from whom it takes its name, but likewiſe of ſeveral as well Kings and Princes as others. As alſo a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of many ſtrange Countries, with their manners, cuſtomes, and commodities: And to conclude, is ſo delightful that none of this nature have excelled it; it being written as well for pleaſure as pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="poem_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:54800:3"/>
            <head>The Contents of the BOOK.</head>
            <l>IN <hi>Cyprus</hi> Iſle liv'd <hi>Theodorus</hi> fam'd,</l>
            <l>In a fair City <hi>Famagoſto</hi> nam'd;</l>
            <l>Extravagant and wild he ſpent his ſtore,</l>
            <l>That by exceſs he grew ſo wondrous <hi>poor,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>That <hi>Fortunatus</hi> all the Sons he had</l>
            <l>Was forc'd to wander as kind fortune led:</l>
            <l>When oft he death and danger did eſcape,</l>
            <l>Encountring Bares or worſe in humane ſhape.</l>
            <l>When as by chance he did Dame <hi>Fortune</hi> meet,</l>
            <l>Who him (loſt in a darkſome Wood) did greet,</l>
            <l>Gave him a Purſe that he ſhould ne'r be poor,</l>
            <l>And bid his Sons likewiſe poſſeſs the ſtore:</l>
            <l>With this he roves the world from coaſt to coaſt,</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Leopoldo</hi> hires (who kills the faithleſs Hoſt)</l>
            <l>To <hi>Cyprus</hi> he returns, his Parents dead,</l>
            <l>There builds a Pallace and a Wife does wed;</l>
            <l>Leaving Two Sons again to Travel bent,</l>
            <l>When in ſtrange Countries ſixteen years he ſpent.</l>
            <l>Returning from the Souldan King does bear</l>
            <l>A Hat (which wiſhing) bares him through the air.</l>
            <l>Returns (and dying) to his Sons bequeaths</l>
            <l>His Hat and Purſe and all their vertues leaves.</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Ampedo</hi> eldeſt, <hi>Andolocia</hi> next,</l>
            <l>Their Mother dyes with grief ſo ſore perplext.</l>
            <l>When <hi>Andolocia</hi> with the Purſe does rome,</l>
            <l>And mild <hi>Ampedo</hi> ſtays content at home.</l>
            <l>After much fame acquir'd in Princes Courts,</l>
            <l>To <hi>England</hi> Andolocia ſtraight reſorts,</l>
            <l>And ſpends his time in feaſting and in ſports.</l>
            <l>Till <hi>Agrippina</hi>'s beauty proves a ſnare,</l>
            <l>And makes him whence his Riches flow declare.</l>
            <l>Then whilſt he is with drowſineſs oppreſt,</l>
            <l>He of his Purſe is quickly diſpoſſeſt.</l>
            <l>Then from his Brother he conveys the Hat,</l>
            <l>With which after much toil the Purſe he got.</l>
            <l>The Princeſs is to <hi>Theodorus</hi> Wed,</l>
            <l>Young <hi>Cyprus</hi> Prince, and to that Court is led.</l>
            <l>There <hi>Andolocia</hi> by his martial feats</l>
            <l>The envy of ſome envious Nobles gets.</l>
            <l>Who in a wood at his return do ſlay</l>
            <l>His Men, and him in a deep Dungeon lay;</l>
            <l>Bereave him of his Purſe and then his life,</l>
            <l>For which 2 Earls did dye to end the ſtrife.</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Ampedo</hi> hearing of his Brothers death,</l>
            <l>Burns his ſwift Hat, and then reſigns his breath.</l>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:54800:3"/>
            <head>THE HISTORY OF FORTUNATUS.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> 
               </head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of the Parentage and Birth of <hi>Fortunatus.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N <hi>Famogoſta</hi> a Famous City in the Iſle of <hi>Cyprus,</hi> lived one <hi>Theodorus</hi> deſcended of Noble Patentage, who by the Deceaſe of his Father, had a plentiful E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate fell into his hands; but he being of a haughty Mind, gave himſelf wholly up to the Pleaſures and Vanity of the World: He aſſociated himſelf with the Great Men of the Country, and lived riotouſly, ſpending his time for the moſt part in Gaming, Hunting, Hawking, and Sumptuous
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:54800:4"/> Entertainments, the which in a ſhort time greatly diminiſhed his Eſtate; which his Friends perceiving, and being much grieved there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at, thought there was no better way to reſtrain his Licentious man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Life, than by matching him to a Wife.</p>
               <p>This being reſolved upon, and he not contradicting the Motion, they ſought for a fair, young and vertuous Lady throughout all the Citys of <hi>Cyprus,</hi> and at laſt in <hi>Nicova</hi> found one that well-liked them, ſhe being Daughter to a Wealthy Merchant, and adorned with all the Perfections that appertain to Womankind, her Name being <hi>Gratiana:</hi> to this Lady by the Conſent of her Father, <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>odorus</hi> was ſhortly married, and for a time lived in great Splen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor, the firſt Year having by her a fair Son, whom they named <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunatus;</hi> but this little or nothing reſtrained his Extravagancies: Inſomuch that in a ſhort time after the Marriage, notwithſtanding the large Portion he had with his Wife, he was brought to extream Poverty, which made him repent, though now too late; ſo that often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times being hunger-pined, and in great want, he looking upon his Son (who by this time was a comely Youth) would ſigh and let fall Tears, which ſo afflicted the Young-man, that he one day de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded the Cauſe, deſiring to know whether he had offended him in ought, the which if he had he would ſtrive to amend it: To whom the ſorrowful Father replied, He had never offended him; but it was the exceeding Penury to which by his Extravagancies he was reduced to that maded as he ſaw: To which the Youth replied, Let not that trouble you, for as for me, I have received ſuch good Education un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der you, that I can ſhift for my ſelf in any place of the World; but he perceiving his Father ſtill troubled, and alwaies ſigh when he looked upon him, he conjectured it was for his ſake, and therefore reſolved to be no longer chargeable to him: Whereupon one Day ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king his Stick in his hand, he went to the Sea-ſide, where he had not ſtaied long, but a Gaſly put to ſhore, in which was the Earl of <hi>Flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> who was returned from <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> they had not been long on ſhore to refreſh themſelves, but the Earl cauſed the Trumpet to ſound, to call his men back into the Galley; which <hi>Fortunatus</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving, and being deſirous to Travel, went to the Earl and offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him his Service: When the Earl perceiving him a goodly Youth,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:54800:4"/> and having by reaſon of ſickneſs, loſt two of his men by the way, he entertained him; when as the Earl and <hi>Fortunatus</hi> being on Board, they ſet Sail, and in a ſhort time arrived at <hi>Venice.</hi>
               </p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>woodcut of Fortunatus and the Earl boarding a ship with two men on it</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>repetitive woodcut of multiple trees</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How <hi>Fortunatus</hi> departed his Country, and how he became greatly eſteemed by the Earl.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>AFter ſome Conteſts with the Winds and Sea, the Galley ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly arrived at <hi>Venice,</hi> where the Earl and his Men landed; and there by the help of <hi>Fortunatus</hi> (who amongſt all his men could onely ſpeak the Language) he bought rich Iewels, and Gold Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broderies, in order to his Marriage, he being to Wed the Duke of <hi>Cleves</hi> Daughter at his return, to whom he had been Contracted before his departure. By theſe and ſuch other Services, <hi>Fortunatus</hi> gained the Love of his Lord; inſomuch that the reſt of the Servants began to envy him: A while after the Earl coming into his own Country, bought all his Servants Horſes, and gave to <hi>Fortuna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> the beſt next what himſelf rod on; ſo that it greatly grieved the reſt of the Servants, who wiſhed the Devil had had the <hi>Italian</hi> before he came into their Lords Service. A while after the Marriage
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:54800:5"/> being Celebrated, a great number of Nobility being preſent, Tilts and Iuſts were prepared, where after the Nobles had done great Feats, the Earl ſet up two Iewels valued at a hundred pounds, for the Servants who ſhould do beſt; upon which <hi>Fortunatus</hi> prepared his Horſe, and ſoon with his Lance overthrew one of them that run againſt him, whereupon he carried away the Prize; then one <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothy</hi> having won the other Iewel, the Servants urged <hi>Timothy</hi> to Iuſt with <hi>Fortunatus,</hi> who ſhould have them both; but in the Conflict <hi>Timothy</hi> was born down Horſe and Man, ſo that <hi>Fortuna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>woodcut of a joust</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>repetitive woodcut of multiple trees</figDesc>
                  </figure> got not onely both the Iewels, but the great Applauſe of the Spectators, and the greater Favour of the Earl, who highly praiſed him, telling them by what chance he had met with him: whereupon the Nobles and Ladies gave him many Preſents; this more and more raiſed the Malice of his Fellow-ſervants againſt him; but when they well perceived that they could do nothing againſt him fairly, they wrought by ſubtilty: for there being amongſt the reſt one <hi>Robert</hi> an ancient Servant to the Earl, who promiſed for Ten Crowns to make <hi>Fortunatus</hi> run away; to this they gladly heark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and every one paid his Dividend moſt joyfully: when this was done, he inſinuates himſelf into the company of <hi>Fortunatus,</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:54800:5"/> more than ordinary kindneſs, carrying him abroad to Treats, and other Meriments, without ſuffering him to pay ought; this <hi>Fortunatus</hi> imagining to proceed from the intire good will he bore him, he gave the greater credit to all he ſaid, not perceiving his ſubtilty: When the Money was almoſt ſpent, and the Servants began to put <hi>Robert</hi> in mind of his Promiſe, he one day taking <hi>Fortunatus</hi> into a private Apartment, after ſeveral Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes, he began to ſigh and look ſad, which <hi>Fortunatus</hi> well no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, demanded the Cauſe, who told him it was for his ſake: then was he earneſt to know the Reaſon; truly ſaid <hi>Robert</hi> it was told me by my ſingular good Friend, who upon a great Penalty enjoyned me Secrecy, but for the Love and good Will I bare to you, I ſhall reveal it. Then thus our Lord intends to Morrow to Ride to <hi>Lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſan,</hi> to wage Law againſt the Earl of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> where for the jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie he had lately conceived of his Chamberlains, leaſt they ſhould either have carnal Copulation with his beateous Wife, or any of her fair Ladies and Gentlewomen that attended her, he is reſolved to have them all Gelded, and though he entirely loves you above any of his Servants, yet he cannot ſerve the reſt ſo while you take part with them in the ſame, you being chief Chamberlain, and the moſt comely amongſt them, after which he will only reveal it ho his Lady, forbidding her to reveal it; but as the manner of Women is, it cannot be expected that ſhe will keep the Secret long; ſo that it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſpread abroad, it will redoun to your utter Diſgrace, if the cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting do not hazard your Life: this I learned from him who is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to Geld you, he telling it me (as thinking I might be one of the Chamberlains) in requital of ſome ſingular Favours I had done him.</p>
               <p>When <hi>Fortunatus</hi> heard this he looked as pale as Death; and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired <hi>Robert</hi> by all the Ties of Friendſhip, that he would be aſſiſting to him in making his eſcape; for ſaid he, I would not be Gelded if my Lord would give me his Earldom: When he talked of Flight, the Hypocrite <hi>Robert</hi> feigned himſelf ſad, and deſired his ſtay, the better to perſwade him into a Belief of what he had related, telling him he was ſorry that ever he had Imparted it to him; but <hi>Fortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natus</hi> ſtanding as it were upon thorns, thought every hour ten, till
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:54800:6"/> he was gone; then <hi>Robert</hi> bid him in what place ſoever he reſided, ſend him a Letter, that when the Earl was ſupplied with Gelded-men, he might give notice to return: But <hi>Fortunatus</hi> replied, he would never return, though he endured never ſuch neceſſity or want. Vpon this <hi>Robert</hi> inwardly cejoyced, and helping him to a horſe, he rod out of the City as if he went on hunting, and having paſſed the Gate, ſet on full ſpeed and never looked behind him, till he thought himſelf out of Danger, and purchaſing another horſe, he ſent back the Earls, leſt upon that account he might be purſued.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How the Earl grieved for the Departure of <hi>Fortunatus;</hi> and what befel him afterwards.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>NO ſooner the flight of <hi>Fortunatus</hi> came to the Earls Ear, but he was exceeding ſorry, muſing with himſelf what ſhould be the Cauſe; but when he could think of none, he demanded of his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants if they were privy to the Occaſion of his Departure, but they denied they knew ought: then he examined his Lady and her Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>women who were there at the ſame time, ſaying, that the Evening be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he was very pleaſant, and had diſcourſed to them about ſeveral Affairs of Women, and other things; at which the Earl marvelled the more, ſaying, Although he could not then learn the true Cauſe of his Departing without taking leave of him, he doubted not but that he ſhould find it out, and he would ſeverely puniſh the Occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioner of it: This terrified <hi>Robert,</hi> ſo that he grew very Melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly, leſt any of the Servants ſhould betray him; and thereupon he took an Oath of Secrecy of them all, and when they were importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate to know by what means he had effected it, he told them a ſtory of his Fathers Advancement by the King of <hi>Cyprus,</hi> quite contrary to what he had practiſed. But to return to <hi>Fortunatus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fortunatus</hi> being on his way, made what ſpéed he could to <hi>Calice,</hi> where eſpying an <hi>Engliſh Ship,</hi> he bargained with the Maſter to Tranſport him into <hi>England,</hi> where arriving, he came to <hi>London,</hi>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:54800:6"/> where he hapned into the company of two young <hi>Cyprus</hi> Merchants, who were ſent over by their Fathers too, with a Ship laden with coſtly Wares, for which they had received great Sums of Money: And now <hi>Fortunatus</hi> being expert in the Manners and Cuſtoms of moſt Countries, became as it were their Tutor or Inſtructor; ſo that they ſpent beyond meaſure, Rioting it all the Day at Taverns, and at Night ſporting it with Harlots, each one ſtriving to out-do the other in Exceſs; nor was <hi>Fortunatus</hi> wanting to ſpend amongſt them: but within a while all their Money being ſpent, their Burom Laſſes forſook them, and all their Iollitry came to an end, which made the Merchants bethink themſelves of Returning home, which they did in the ſame Ship they came in, though with heavy hearts and empty Purſes, leaving <hi>Fortunatus</hi> behind them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How <hi>Fortunatus</hi> became a Servant, and how one wicked <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew</hi> by murdering a Gentleman in the houſe of <hi>Fortunatus</hi>'s Maſter, brought the whole Family in great trouble.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>FOrtunatus</hi> being bare of Money and in a ſtrange Country, knew not well what courſe to take; but at laſt reſolved to get over into <hi>France,</hi> but wanted Money to pay his Paſſage; when gorng to a Harlot on whom he ſpent the greateſt part of his money, he deſired her to lend him two Crowns, telling her that he was to go over Sea to fetch Four hundred Crowns that his Vncle owed him; but ſhe would by no means lend him any, nor ſcarcely make him drink, but ſent him away with flouts: Then ſeeing his former Folly, he wiſhed, (though too late) that he had kept his Money, and not have ſpent it upon ſuch an ungrateful Baggage; ſo that not having Money to pay for his Paſſage, he betook himſelf to the Service of one <hi>Jeroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus Roberti,</hi> a <hi>Florentine</hi> Merchant in <hi>Lombard-ſtreet,</hi> where he lived with great Credit, pleaſing his Maſter beyond meaſure by his Diligence and towardneſs, and in a ſhort time gained not onely the Love of his Miſtris, but of all the Servants: Inſomuch that his
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:54800:7"/> Maſter not onely intruſted him with all his Caſh, but employed him in his main Affairs; as taking in his Merchandize, and other things of ſecret and weighty Concernment, whereby he not onely advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged himſelf, but alſo by his faithful Diſcharge of the Truſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to him; he greatly advantaged his Maſter, inſomuch that he became dear to him; but he had not long continued in his Service, before an Extravagant <hi>Florentine</hi> came to his Maſter, whoſe Name was <hi>Andrew,</hi> the Son of a very reſponſible Merchant, who had been fitted out with a Ship and all manner of Merchandize, the which he had ſold and imbezled at a laviſh Rate; and thereupon was driven to extream Poverty, which obliged him to live by his Wits; ſo that bethinking himſelf, he counterfeited Bills of Exchange, and by that means ſo drained his Father of what Monies he had, that in expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation of what ſhould be returned by Merchandize, he utterly Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poveriſhed him; the which when he perceived, and that no more Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney was to be had, he betook himſelf to Shifts, and being at <hi>Bruges,</hi> the place were he had ſpent the greateſt part of his Money, he began to bethink himſelf that it was in vain for him to return, by reaſon of the great Injury he had done his Father, and then again conſidering that thoſe whom he had ſpent his Monies upon, began to ſlight him, and that he could neither borrow any, nor be truſted for ſuch conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient things as were appertaining to the Supply of Nature, he much condoled and bewailed his ſad Condition whereinto by reaſon of his Extravagancy he was fallen, and reſolved whatever bety'd him to return to his Father; when in his Travels homeward he came to the City of <hi>Turene</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> where by his Hoſt he under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood that a Merchant of <hi>London,</hi> upon a ſpiteful Accuſation, lay in Irons in a dark Dungeon, and that he being very rich, would plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifully reward any One that would go over into <hi>England</hi> and ſolicite his Buſineſs, ſo that he might be delivered. At this News <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew</hi> rejoyced not a little, and thereupon asked his Hoſt whether free acceſs might be had to this Merchant? To which the Hoſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, that for a ſmall piece of money he might ſo far prevail with the Keeper as to admit him to the ſpeech of the Merchant: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon he reſolved to make the beſt of his time, preparing a <hi>Ducket</hi> for that purpoſe, for which the Keeper joyfully let him in; when he
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:54800:7"/> was entred the Priſon or Dungeon, by a Light that he had with him, he eſpied the Merchant who lay faſt Fettered in Irons, to whom he addreſſed himſelf in <hi>Engliſh;</hi> upon which the Merchant was not a little over-joyed, asking him if he knew ſuch and ſuch Perſons, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong whom he named <hi>Jeronimo Roberti;</hi> to which he replied, that he knew him very well, and that he had not onely been acquainted with him in <hi>England,</hi> but likewiſe in the City of <hi>Florence;</hi> then he ſhewed him the Cauſe of his Impriſonment, which was for Forging the King of <hi>Englands</hi> Paſs-port, deſiring him out of all love that he would ſpeedily repair to <hi>London;</hi> and ſhew unto his Friends in what a ſad condition he lay, and how pitifully he had been handled ſince his coming into that Priſon, and to deſire them to ſolicite his Enlargement, for which he would not only think himſelf Infinitely Obliged to him, but would reward him with Five hundred Crowns.</p>
               <p>At this welcom News <hi>Andrew</hi> did not a lictle rejoyce, ſo that ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king ſome monies of him to bear his Charges, he departed, promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to do his beſt in order to his Delivery; and thereupon took Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping for <hi>England,</hi> and coming to <hi>London,</hi> he made it his buſineſs to go from place to place to the Merchants Friends, as alſo to the Court, where he underſtood he could not be releaſed unleſs he payed a Fine of Three thouſand Crowns, the which <hi>Jeronimo Roberti</hi> promiſed to lay down upon Security: So that <hi>Andrew</hi> going from place to place to get one to enter into Bonds for the Sum, at laſt underſtood that the King having married his Daughter to the Duke of <hi>Burgundia,</hi> reſolved to make her a Preſent of the richeſt Iewels that might be got, having already cauſed his Iewellers to make them, and deliver them to a truſty Knight, who was appointed to convey them to her. At this <hi>Andrew</hi> inwardly rejoyced; and now deſpairing of getting Security of the Sum of Money demanded, he reſolved not to loſe his labour of coming into <hi>England;</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon by his frequenting the Court, got acquainted with the Iewel-Bearer, and finding out a fit Opportunity, told him that he was by Birth a <hi>Florentine,</hi> and by Profeſſion a Ieweller; and foraſmuch as he heard the King of <hi>England</hi> was minded to purchaſe the beſt Iewels he could get, he had come out of his own Country with a parcel of ſuch Iewels as he believed the like were not to be had in
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:54800:8"/> 
                  <hi>England;</hi> and thereupon deſired the Gentleman to let him ſee thoſe he had in charge, the which he readily did, not dreaming of his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign.</p>
               <p>When <hi>Andrew</hi> had well viewed them, and by their fairneſs could not imagin leſs but that they were of a great value, he told the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman that many of his exceeded them, not only in Luſtre but in Virtue, as being Stones of a different Nature, eſpecially one Lock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et of Black Diamonds which he had purchaſed of a <hi>Jew,</hi> who lately came from the <hi>Indies:</hi> upon this the Gentleman told him, that if he might but ſee them, he doubted not but that the King would at leaſt purchaſe ſome of them, and thereupon he deſired him to ſtay and dine with him, the which he did, and after dinner, <hi>Andrew</hi> invited the Gentleman to come the next Day to <hi>Jeronimus Roberti</hi>'s Houſe to dine with him, and that there he ſhould have a ſight of them: this he conſented to, and leave taken, <hi>Andrew</hi> went to <hi>Jeronimus Roberti</hi> and informed him, that he had met with a Gentleman of a good Eſtate, who for the love he bore to the Merchant would become bound for the 3000 Crowns, and withal told him; that he intended to be there the next Day, and therefore he adviſed him to prepare a dinner to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain him, and not to ſpeak any thing to him about his Surety-ſhip till he ſhould give the Signet; to this <hi>Jeronimus</hi> conſented, as well knowing he ſhould have good Intereſt for his Money. The next Day the Gentleman came, and the Table being ſpread, they ſat down to dinner, and there diſcourſed of Divers Affairs, when after they were riſen from the Table, <hi>Andrew</hi> took the Gentleman by the hand and led him up ſtairs pretending to ſhew him his Iewels, and there ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king his opportunity before the Gentleman was aware, with a Dagger that he had provided for the purpoſe, he ſtobb'd him, ſo that he ſunk down dead, and then taking his Signet and his Keys he got away uneſpyed, and haſted to the Gentlemans Houſe, where meeting with his Wife, he told her that her Husband had received Orders inſtantly to depart for the Duke of <hi>Burgundies</hi> Court, and that ſhe muſt ſend the Iewels, by the ſame token there was his Signet and his Keys of his Cabinet, which the Gentlewoman taking of <hi>Andrew,</hi> went and unlocked the Cabinet, and, not finding the Iewels there, returned and told him, that her Husband muſt come and look them himſelf; for they
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:54800:8"/> were not there: upon this <hi>Andrew</hi> departed much perplexed that he had miſſed of his aim, and long time he Pondered whether he ſhould return to <hi>Jeronimus,</hi> or fly; during which ſpace, <hi>Jeronimus</hi> coming into his Hall, perceived blood to drop through the Sealing, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon commanded his Servants to run up and find out the cauſe, where they no ſooner came but they found the Gentleman Murthered, at which they were much amazed, and haſted down to relate the ſame to their Maſter: who took an hateing that any ſuch thing ſhould be done in his Houſe, and knew not what to do in the buſineſs as being but a ſtranger in <hi>England,</hi> and not well acquainted with the Laws.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How <hi>Andrew</hi> returned to <hi>Jeronimus</hi>'s Houſe and diſpoſing of the dead body, afterward made his eſcape; and how the Murther being found out, <hi>Jeronimus</hi> and all his Servants were Impriſoned.</p>
               </argument>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>woodcut of Andrew carrying a dead man over his shoulder; woodcut repeated on p. 41</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>The Gentleman being two days miſſing at Court, many began to wonder, and the third day acquainted the King thereof, who began to miſtruſt: that the great value of his charge might have made him falſe though otherwiſe, a Gentleman of undoubted Reputation and Fidelity; upon which a Meſſenger was ſent to his Houſe to In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire for him, and was informed by his Wife, that ſhe had not ſeen him in three days: but that at his departure he went in the Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of a <hi>Florentine,</hi> who pretended to have great ſtore of Iewels at the Houſe of one <hi>Jeronimus Roberti</hi> a <hi>Florentine,</hi> Merchant in <hi>Lom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bard-ſtreet,</hi> and that a while after their departure, the ſame perſon came with her Husbands Keys and Ring, deſiring her to ſend the Iewels, but ſhe looking for them in his Cabinet, found them not there.</p>
               <p>With this anſwer they returned to the King, who was greatly diſpleaſed, but that he might not ſeem over raſhly to cenſure the Fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of the Knight, although he concluded he was fled, he gave order that nothing more ſhould be done in it till the end of two days, in which ſpace <hi>Fortunatus</hi> returning from on Ship-board (where he had
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:54800:9"/> been taking an account of the ladeing) perceived not only his Maſter, but all his fellow Servants very melancholly; upon which, he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded of the Maid what was the cauſe of ſuch their ſuddain alterati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to whom ſhe anſwered (as having before-hand premeditated an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe) that her Maſter had received a Letter of the Death of a dear Friend of his, which had occaſioned that ſadneſs in him; and that with him the reſt Simpathized as is the Cuſtom of their Country, but that he not being his near Relation, he would not go into Mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for him, with which <hi>Fortunatus</hi> was well pleaſed. But now the two days being expired, and no tidings of the Gentleman; the King in a great rage ſent his Purſevants to ſearch his Houſe, who broke o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen as many Trunks, Cheſts and Cabinets, as they found locked, in it found not the Iewels: upon which, at the Supplication of the Gentlewoman (who ſaid ſhe verily believed her Husband was Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered) they went to the Houſe of <hi>Jeronimus,</hi> where having the Kings Warrant, they apprehended him and all his Family upon Suſpicion of Murther, but they all denied it, ſaying: Indeed there was ſuch a man there, but that he departed thence in the Company of the Perſon who brought him thither, and that ſince they ſaw him not: but this excuſe availed not, for they all (being nine in number, of which <hi>Fortunatus</hi> was one) were delivered to the Sheriffs, who carryed them to <hi>Newgate,</hi> where they were kept aſunder, and were ſtrictly examined, but they all declared as before: as for <hi>Fortunatus,</hi> he was ignorant of the matter and therefore could not confeſs, upon which the Sheriffs were ordered to ſearch <hi>Jeronimus</hi>'s Houſe, the which they accordingly did, and looked in all the Cheſts, Trunks, Cloſets, Cellers, Pantries and Stables, but found not the dead Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and ſo were about to depart, when one amongſt the reſt having a Torch in his hand, lighted ſome Paper and threw it down into the Privy, whereby reaſon of the ſhallowneſs of the Ordure, the Legs of the party Murthered appeared, he being caſt in with his Head down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, which he no ſooner perceived by the Light, but he called to the reſt, telling them that he had found the Murthered Corps, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon they all coming together drew it out, and after having cleanſed it with Water, they layed it in the Street before the Door of <hi>Jeroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus,</hi> for to be ſeen of all People, who with great Deteſtation and ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:54800:10"/> of their Heads abhorred the Fact: as alſo a Meſſenger was ſent to acquaint the King what they had found, upon which he gave order for the Racking <hi>Jeronimus,</hi> and the reſt, to force them to confeſs where the Iewels were, for he ſuppoſed that they had Murthered him for the Iewels; when they being ſtretched upon the Rack, and in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding torment, confeſſed the true manner of the Murther as it is before recited. But <hi>Fortunatus,</hi> although he was tormented with the reſt, could not give any account of the Murther by reaſon of his abſence when the Fact was committed; but as for the Iewels, they all proteſted they knew not any thing of them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How <hi>Jeronimus Roberti,</hi> and ſeven of his Servants were Hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for the Murther, and how <hi>Fortunatus</hi> was ſaved at the Place of Execution.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>NOtwithſtanding they made their Confeſſion, how and upon what caſion the Murther was Committed, it availed them nothing; for the King iſſued out a Commiſſion to try them, where cheir own Confeſſions and the finding of the Murthered Corps in the Houſe being proved againſt them they were found Guilty, and being Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, were ſhortly carried to the Place of Execution; a pair of<figure>
                     <figDesc>woodcut of nine men and a king at the gallows</figDesc>
                  </figure> Gallows being built for that purpoſe, where they were urged to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs where the Iewels were, but they declared they never ſaw them,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:54800:10"/> nor could they give any account of them. So that firſt <hi>Jeronimus</hi> was turned off, and then an other, ſo one after another till none were left but the Cook and <hi>Fortunatus,</hi> who now began to make a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand wry faces, as giving themſelves over for gone, but when the Cooke came to be turned off, he deſired to ſpeak a word or two, which was the readyer granted becauſe they ſuppoſed he might tell what was become of the Iewels; but ſilence being made, he ſaid <hi>Fortunatus</hi> was altogether innocent of the Fact as being abroad about his occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions when it was done, and that he knew not of the Body being in the Privy, by reaſon they all concealed it from him; and therefore if he did dye, he dyed innocently and wrongfully. At the hearing of this, the People prevailed ſo far with the Sheriff, as to ſtay till the King might be Advertized of what had been related; who upon the hearing thereof, and at the earneſt Suit of ſome Ladys (who had caſt their Eyes upon <hi>Fortunatus,</hi> and ſeeing him a goodly Youth, were moved to pitty him) the King ſent his Mandate to the Sheriff to ſave his Life; who thereupon, after he had faſtned the reſt in Chains to the Gallows, brought back <hi>Fortunatus,</hi> and in a while after ſet him at Liberty.</p>
               <p>At that time alſo the King commanded <hi>Jeronimus</hi>'s Houſe to be ſpoiled, where every one took what beſt liked him; of which the reſt of the <hi>Florentines</hi> hearing they were ſore afraid, and leaſt the Multitude who were greatly incenced againſt them ſhould break into their Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and ſpoil them alſo, they layed their Heads together and at laſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded to raiſe a conſiderable Summ of Money and lend to the King to regain his good Affection towards them, upon which they were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived into Favour, and a Proclamation put out in their behalfs, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biding any to abuſe them, but that they ſhould let them freely Traf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fick as before.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:54800:11"/>
               <head>CHAP. VII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How afterward all the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ewels were found by the Widdow of the Murthered Gentleman, and by her reſtored to the King.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>AFter the Execution, the King ſuppoſing the Murtherer to have carried away the Iewels he put forth his Proclamation; offering 1000 Crowns to any that would diſcover them or return them again. Further, he ſent to all the noted deellers in the neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring Kingdoms, to ſtop any ſuch Iewels if they ſhould be offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be ſould; but after all this they were found under the bed of the Murthered Gentleman; the manner of their being diſcovered was thus. About a Month after the Murther the Gentleman being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cently buryed, ſeveral of the Neighbours came to Comfort the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſolate Widdow, and perceiving her ſtill to be troubled for the loſs of her Husband, one amongſt the reſt who was in the ſame condition with her but of a merrier temper, bid her chear up, and by thinking of the Livſng put the Dead out of her Remembrance, telling her that the beſt way to do it, was to remove her Bed into an other Chamber, ſo that the Remembrance of paſt pleaſures might be forgot, and that by fixing her thoughts upon ſome luſty young Lover, the Remembrance of her Dead Husband might be done away, adding that ſhe had done the ſame, and found the greateſt Conſolation therein; but the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woman replyed, O how ſhall I forget ſo good a Husband, who ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred me as dear as his Life? had he been bad I might have done it; yet after their departure ſhe went to remove her Bed, and had ſcarce drawn it two foot, but under it ſhe eſpyed a little Casket the which ſhe took up, and having opened it, ſhe (to her great joy) found all the Iewels therein; and thereupon ſent to a Kinſman of hers whom ſhe could beſt truſt to ask his advice how ſhe ſhould beſtow them, and when he came, ſhe firſt told him the manner of her finding them, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards ſhewed them to him; who after ſome conſideration, advi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed her to carry them her ſelf to the King, ſaying, that if they were offered to be ſold they would be ſtoped, and then her Life might come
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:54800:11"/> in danger: to this advice of her Coſins ſhe gladly conſented, ſo that away thy went, and after ſome Attendance got to be admitted into the Kings preſence, where kneeling before him, ſhe ſaid, Moſt Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Liege, I am come humbly to preſent you with the Iewels, for which my dear Husband loſt his life. As I was removing my Bed this day, I found them under it, and with that ſhe delivered the Casket, which the King opening and perceiving they were all there, he greatly rejoyced; ſaying, Foraſmuch as you have been thus faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, you ſhall not go unrewarded: As for the loſs of your Husband, I, as well as you are not a little grieved, therefore to repair the loſs I will chooſe you another; and thereupon called a Knight, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded him to marry her, the which the Knight conſenting to, as not being willing to diſoblige the King the Ceremonies of their Marriage was celebrated in the Kings preſence; and now ſaid the King, I Endow you with my Mannor of <hi>Woodſtock,</hi> with a Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand pounds a year to continue Yours during both your Lives, and thereupon he diſmiſſed them: ſo that the Bride departed joyful that ſuch good Fortune had befallen, and went to all her Goſſips to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint them with the ſame, giving the Widow many Thanks for her ſeaſonable Advice, ſaying, If ſhe had not removed the Bed, the Iewels might have ſtood there time out of mind, telling her that ſhe would always make uſe of her Counſel for the future.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VIII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How <hi>Fortunatus</hi> having got over Sea loſt himſelf, in a Wood in <hi>France;</hi> and of his Encountring with, and killing a wild Bear that came to devour him.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>THe dread of Hanging and his narrow Eſcape, ſo terrified <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunatus,</hi> that he did not think himſelf ſafe ſo long as he trod upon <hi>Engliſh</hi> Ground: Whereupon he made what haſte he could to paſs the Seas, ſo that having got on Board a Ship in which his dead Maſter uſed to Trafick, ſhe ſet Sail for France, where they ſet him on ſhoar; and now he being Monileſs, thought the beſt way
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:54800:12"/> was to get him a Maſter, but after a long Inquiring, finding none that would Entertain him, he reſolved to Travel further; when being belated in a large Foreſt, where few Paſſengers travelled, he ſtruck out of the Road into a Croſs-way, which led him into further Inranglements: for not being able to find any end of the Wood, when Evening came, he ſat him down and began to lament himſelf, being both Hungry and a Thirſt; yet there he ſate, not daring to ſleep for fear of the wild Beaſts, which he heard make hidious noiſe from many parts, and who in the Night uſually range for Prey; but that Night eſcaping any Encounter with them, the next Day he got up and went onwards, but at laſt was ſo intangled in the Thickets, that he could hardly go either backwards or forwards; but at laſt he found ſome Water, of which, drinking freely out of his Hat, he made his Dinner of Berries and Cornel, and ſo paſſed over that day.</p>
               <p>The next Night the Moon began to ſhine, and as he was ſitting, and greatly bewailing his Condition, he heard a ruſtling in the Leaves, looking up he perceived a huge Bear coming towards him, whoſe ugly ſight did not a little terrifie him; whereupon to avoid her fury, he got up the Tree that ſtood next him, thinking to continue
<figure>
                     <figDesc>repetitive woodcut of single tree</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>woodcut of Fortunatus stabbing a bear with a sword</figDesc>
                  </figure> there till ſuch time as the Bear was paſſed by, but ſhe having eſpied him, began to climb the Tree after him, and withal made ſuch a hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:54800:12"/> noiſe, that ſhe cauſed ſeveral other Beaſts to repair thither; The Bear having got up the hardeſt part of the Tree, purſued <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunatus</hi> ſtill as he climed higher, the which he perceiving, plucked up a Courage, and drawing his Sword, was reſolved to ſtand to it Manfully,: The Bear came at him with open Mouth. and he ſtill as ſhe reached at him with her Paws, wounded her in one place or other, till at length ſhe fell down, and in the fall was ſo bruiſed, that ſhe lay as dead; which <hi>Fortunatus</hi> perceiving, and well noting that all the other Beaſts were withdrawn, he came down, and thruſt his Sword into the Bears Heart, after which being almoſt ſtarved with Hunger, he flead part of her, and cutting off ſome of her Fleſh eat it, by which being ſtrengthned, he the next Morning got up, and reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to ſearch his way out; when at laſt coming into the great Road where he was at firſt, he met with a <hi>Walloon,</hi> who directed him the neareſt way; inſomuch that in an hours Travelling he got out of the Foreſt and came to the City of <hi>Orleance,</hi> where he met with ſome refreſhment, but had like to have paid dear for his coming thither, as in the next Chapter will appear.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IX.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How <hi>Fortunatus</hi> falling aſleep in a Porch in the City of <hi>Orle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance</hi> had a bloody Knife put into his Sleeve, and how he being found with it was accuſed of the Murther of a Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlewoman, and narrowly eſcaped; the Perſon that did the Murther being broken upon the Wheel for the ſame.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>IN the City of <hi>Orleance</hi> in the Kingdom of <hi>France,</hi> lived one <hi>James D'Bret</hi> a rich Merchant, who had a fair and beautiful young Gentlewoman to his Daughter, named <hi>Mary D'Bret,</hi> who being a conſiderable Fortune, had many Suitors, and amongſt the reſt, a Merchant of the ſame place, whoſe Name was <hi>Anthony Mont<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples;</hi> it's true, he was a very comely Gentleman, but being young he was drawn away by lude Company to all manner of Extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancies, which made the Father of the Damſel that he would not
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:54800:13"/> hearken to the giving him his Daughter, although the Maid could have been well content to have loved him for his Perſon, but being charged by her Father upon his Bleſſing and the Ties of her Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, not to permit his farther Addreſſes, ſhe not onely gave him his Anſwer at his next coming, but alſo would not from that time forward admit him to ſee her, unleſs by accident he met her in the Street, and then as much as in her lay ſhe would ſhun him, which made him turn his former Love into Hatred, and the ſtuddy of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge; inſomuch that within awhile after, he having certain notice by ſome of her Servants (whom he bribed to ſend him word how things went from time to time) that within two daies ſhe was to be Married to a Knights eldeſt Son, who lived at a Village about four Miles from the City: He being moved by the Inſtigation of the Devil, reſolved to hinder the Match whatever it coſt him, and thereupon he diſcloſed his Mind to one <hi>Saggue</hi> a bloody Villain, and one with whom he often kept company; who adviſed him, that ſince the Gentlewoman had proved falſe to him in breaking her Promiſe, and now was reſolved by marrying another to fruſtrate all his hopes, it was but juſt that ſince he could not enjoy her himſelf, to hinder any other from doing the ſame; for ſaies he, It will ſurely grieve you to think what pleaſure your Rival enjoyes, whilſt you ſuffer pain and torment; nay more, to think how they will flout and jeer you at their Merry-makings, and often laugh you to ſcorn for being ſo fooliſh to beflow upon her ſuch liberal Gifts, and all to no purpoſe; nay, and that your Rival ſhould have them at his diſpoſe.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>repetitive woodcut of single tree</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>woodcut of murderer planting knife on Fortunatus</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>Now by this time the whole City was Alarm'd with the piteous Out-cries of the Servants, who were upon the purſuit of the Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therers, who ran here and there ſearching and inquiring, as not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing certain by reaſon of the many turnings which way he fled; when at laſt one of them coming to the Porch where <hi>Fortunatus</hi> lay ſtill aſleep, he cried out, Here he is, here he is, I have found him, I have found him; for indeed <hi>Fortunatus</hi> had the bad Luck to have a Suit of Cloaths on at that time not unlike to the Murtherers, by which the Maid that let him in deſcribed him to the reſt.</p>
               <p>At the Noiſe and Out-cries they made, <hi>Fortunatus</hi> ſuddenly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woak, when ſtarting up in a great Amazement, the Knife dropped out of his Sleeve, which they taking up, and perceiving to be ſtill bloody, they concluded abſolutely that he had murther'd their Miſtris; and thereupon dragging him through the Streets, railing upon him, and threatning him with a thouſand Deaths, without giving him the leaſt knowledge what it was for, when they were come before the Magiſtrate, they declared what had hapned, ſhewing the Knife they had found about him, the Maid likewiſe ſwore it was he; whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the people cried out, Hang him, hang him: Inſomuch that though he pleaded Innocence, and made many Excuſes, he could not be heard but away he was ſent to Priſon, and laid in Irons, and in a ſhort time after was condemned to be broke upon the Wheel; when it ſo chanced that three daies before the Murtherer was apprehended on ſuſpicion of another Murther which he had committed; for which being extreamly wracked and at the point of Death, he did not onely confeſs that, but this alſo for which <hi>Fortunatus</hi> was to ſuffer, telling the manner, and what induced him to do it, and how that upon his flight he found <hi>Fortunatus,</hi> and put the Knife into his Sleeve as he ſlept: This Confeſſion coming to the Iudges Ear, he gave order to ſtay Execution two daies longer, and in the mean time ſent for the Murtherer and <hi>Fortunatus,</hi> as likewiſe the Maid who had ſeen him, and ſetting them both before her, bid her tell which was the Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therer; upon which after ſome pauze, ſhe ſaid, She now well percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:54800:14"/> ſhe had been miſtaken as to what ſhe had before ſworn to, in rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to <hi>Fortunatus,</hi> avowing the other to be the man, and that ſhe not only knew him, by his voice, but by a Scar in his Face, and he being no longer able to conceal his Guilt, he told them all the Paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges how he came to the Gentlewoman with a forged Letter, the which he wrote himſelf, and how he was hired for 200 Crowns by <hi>Montpeſs,</hi> upon which the Letter being there, the Iudge ordred him to write again, the which he did; and then they being compared, it plainly appeared to be his hand: Whereupon the Iudge thanked God who had made ſuch a ſeaſonable diſcovery of the Truth, and thereupon ſent and apprehended <hi>Montpeſs,</hi> who finding the other, and confeſſed the whole Matter, for which within a ſhort time after <hi>Montpeſs</hi> was beheaded, and broken upon the Wheel; but <hi>Fortuna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> ſet free, and the people that a little before had Exclaimed againſt him, pitied him for his wrongful ſuffering, and thereupon made a Purſe amongſt themſelves, and gathered him Sir Crowns, the which he taking very thankfully, departed the City, giving praiſe to God who had ſo miraculouſly wrought his Deliverance.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IX.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How <hi>Fortunatus</hi> travelling through a Foreſt, was met by Dame <hi>Fortune,</hi> and how ſhe gave him a Purſe that continually ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied his Expences.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>FOrtunatus</hi> being got out of the City of <hi>Orleance,</hi> took his way towards <hi>Paris,</hi> when travelling through a huge Foreſt, he on his right-hand perceived a beautiful Creature in female Habit, ſitting under a broad ſpreading Beech-tree with a Vail over her Eyes, who as he came near, aroſe and croſſed him in his way, at which he rejoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced not a little, for he had thought there had been nought but Bears and wild Beaſts in the place, but looking ſtedfaſtly upon her he began to ponder whether ſhe might not be a Fary, or bodily ſhape compoſed by Deluſion: But whilſt he was in this doubt, ſhe taking him by the Hand, gently asked him whether he was going, upon which he
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:54800:15"/> told her, deſireing her that ſhe would accompany him out of the Wood.</p>
               <p>To which ſhe replied, ſhe might not go with him, but that ſhe would do more for him than any on earth had ever done: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon <hi>Fortunatus</hi> gave her many thanks, and deſired to know her Name, and what ſhe was, and her Buſineſs, in ſo deſart a place; to whom ſhe anſwered, my Name is <hi>Fortune,</hi> and here I am placed by him who made all things, and therefore has power to diſpoſe of them as it beſt pleaſeth him: by his Commiſſion I am here placed, to diſtribute Six things, according as the Influence of the Stars by his appointment does direct: the which are theſe; <hi>Wiſdom, Health, long Life, Beauty, Strength,</hi> and <hi>Riches:</hi> and now is the Moment of Choice, therefore make no delay, for in this caſe the Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity being over-ſlipped, returns not again in an Age: Be free, and take for asking any of theſe which ſhall ſeem moſt pleaſing to you.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>woodcut of Fortunatus meeting Dame Fortune</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>repetitive woodcut of multiple trees</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>This ſaid, <hi>Fortunatus</hi> bowed low, and promiſed to perform all ſhe had commanded him: And as for this Day I will yearly keep it Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred, and Liberally beſtow Alms; nay, I will moreover beſtow a large Portion on ſome unmarried Virgin, in order to her being diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed of in Marriage: Then he deſired her to lead him out of the Wood, which ſhe promiſed, and thereupon ordred him to follow her; when as ſhe led him into a great Road, and willed him to go ſtraight forwards, neither turning to the right or the left, nor ſo much as to look back to ſee what was become of her; whenas ſhe no ſooner part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from him, but ſhe vaniſhed: Then <hi>Fortunatus</hi> travelling about three hours, came to the end of the Wood, where lifting up his eyes, he beheld a fair Houſe, and being deſirous to refreſh himſelf there, for he perceived it was an Inn, he put his hand into his Purſe, to try if what had been related, were true, and thereupon pulled out 10 Pieces of Gold, at which he greatly rejoyced and entring the Inn, called for Meat and Drink of the beſt; and by reaſon the Hoſt began to miſteuſt him, as being mean in Apparel, he pulled out two Crowns and gave him them before-hand, whereupon the Hoſt joyfully ſpread the Table with ſuch choice Proviſion as the Houſe would affoard.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:54800:16"/>
               <head>CHAP. X.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How <hi>Fortunatus</hi> at his Departure from the Inn, bought three fair Horſes which Earl <hi>Rodolphus</hi> had before cheapned, for which he was Impriſoned, and narrowly eſcaped his life.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>WHen <hi>Fortunatus</hi> had fufficiently taken his Repaſt, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with greatly refreſhed himſelf after three days continuance in the Inn, he perceived in the Stable exceeding rich Trappins, with all manner of Furniture for a Horſeman, and demanded of his Hoſt to what or whoſe Horſe they did belong, to none ſays the Hoſt, for they are left here to be ſold; then ſaid <hi>Fortunatus,</hi> what is the Price of them; 50 Crowns ſaid the Hoſt, Here is your Money ſaid <hi>Fortunatus;</hi> and ſo taking them, he departed; when travelling forwards ſome di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance thence, he eſpyed a great Village with a Caſtle in it, ſtanding upon a Hill, and thither he repaired with all ſpeed, as hoping there to light of a good Horſe, the which in his former Inn he could not do; when he came thither, he asked for the beſt Inn in the Town, and being directed to it, he ſat him down, and caſted for Proviſion, which his Hoſt brought him, then falling into diſcourſe, he asked him, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he knew not of any good Horſes that were to be ſold thereabouts, to which the Hoſt replyed, that there were three exceeding fair Horſes which had been lately brought to that Town by a Merchant, intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to diſpoſe of them at the Entertainment that was to be made by the Duke of <hi>Orleance,</hi> upon the account of his Wedding with the fair <hi>Iſſabella,</hi> Daughter to the King of <hi>Arragon;</hi> then was <hi>Fortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natus</hi> deſirous to ſee them, but the Hoſt told him that the Earl <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolphus</hi> had bidden 300 Crowns for them, and that the Merchant refuſed to take under 300 Crowns; no matter for the Price, ſaid <hi>Fortunatus,</hi> if ſo I but like them; and thereupon he deſired his Hoſt to go with him to the place where they were, which he did, and ſmiled as he went, to think how he ſhould loſe his labour, for he did not imagine <hi>Fortunatus</hi> had Money to purchaſe them; but coming to the Merchant after having well view'd them, <hi>Fortunatus</hi> drew out the Money, and payed it down, and had the Horſes delivered to him,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:54800:16"/> the which he and his Hoſt conveyed to the Inn, where he gave order for rich Saddles to be made, and ſuch Furniture as was wanting, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring the Hoſt likewiſe to hearken out for two truſty Servants, whom he would furniſh with all things neceſſary; but whilſt he was making theſe Preparations, the Earl ſent as much Money as was demanded for the Horſes: When finding that they were gone, he grew exceeding angry, and ſent again to enquire who he was that durſt buy them out of his hands; and having underſtood at what Inn they were, he ſent his Servants thither, who coming to the Hoſt, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded if ſuch Horſes were in his Stables; to which he anſwered, Yes: Then ſaid they, our Lord has ſent to know the man that durſt to buy them out of his hands; Why truly ſaid the Hoſt, he is a ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and came in by accident; when amongſt other things, he asked me, whether any good Horſes were to be ſold thereabouts? and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly I told him; but did not think by his Garb he was able to buy an Aſs: As for Furniture he brought it with him, but how he came by it, I know not. Nay, ſaid the Servant, in all likelihood he has robbed and murther'd ſome Gentleman upon the Road, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon he departed in a great rage.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How the Earl cauſed <hi>Fortunatus</hi> to be apprehended, and caſt into Priſon, till he gave an account how he came by his Money; and was obliged to deliver the Horſes, and Three hundred Crowns.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>THe Earl having notice of all that had paſſed, ſent immediately to apprehend <hi>Fortunatus</hi> in his Inn, who then by the Counſel of his Hoſt, was preparing to depart; but having ſeized <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>im, they brought him before their Lord, who after many reproachful words, demanded whence he was. and how he came by ſo much Money, as to buy ſuch high priz'd Horſes out of his hands: As to the Firſt, he anſwered, That he was the Son of a poor Courtier of the City of <hi>Famagoſta</hi> in the Iſle of <hi>Cyprus:</hi> As to the ſecond, he ſaid, What
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:54800:17"/> Money he had, he came honeſtly by it, and therefore ought not to be queſtioned about it, unleſs any could prove to the contrary; adding, that he never yet wronged any body of one Farthing: But the Earl angerly told him, that it was not likely ſuch a Fellow as he ſhould have ſo much Money, unleſs he had robbed or murthered ſome perſon for it; and thereupon ordred him to be faſtned to the Rack, in order to force him to a Confeſſion; yet he reſolved rather to ſuffer the worſt Extremity, than to confeſs the ſecret Vertue of his fortunate Purſe; but being put to exceeding Torture, he deſired them to take him from off the Rack, and he would confeſs; the which they did, and brought him before the Earl from out the Priſon, where when he had firſt begged Mercy, he ſaid, As I Yeſterday was travelling in a Foreſt, ſo chanced, that I found a Purſe with 620 Crowns in it: In what Foreſt, ſaid the Earl? A Foreſt about four Miles from this place; Why you Varlet, then ſaid the Earl with a ſtern Countenance, will you rob me of my Right? for know, that I am Lord of the Foreſt, it and that whatever is found there, appertains to me: I knew not that ſaid <hi>Fortunatus,</hi> and therefore humbly crave your pardon; but ſaid the Earl, you ſhall be made to know it e're you depart, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore firſt tell me what is become of the Purſe and Money? As for the Purſe, replyed <hi>Fortunatus,</hi> I took the Money out of it, and threw it into a Brook that runs through the Foreſt; but if it ſhould pleaſe your Honour to take the reſt of the Money, here it is: That ſhall not ſerve, ſaid the Earl, for I will not onely take your Money, but your Life; and therefore againſt to Morrow prepare for your Execution.</p>
               <p>This made <hi>Fortunatus</hi> exceeding ſad, and began to wiſh that he had choſen wiſdom inſtead of riches, by which he eaſily might have eſcaped ſuch troubles, but ſeeing that power and tyranny would have its way, fell upon his Knees, and with tears beſought the Earl to ſpare his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ife, and take both the Horſes and the Mony; for, ſaid he, what will it avail you to take away my Life that am ſuch a miſerable Creature? but if you ſpare me, I ſhall ever extole your Clemency and Goodneſs.</p>
               <p>This and the intreaty of the Earls Servants, but eſpecially the Counteſſes Gentlewomen, moved him to relent, ſo that having taken
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:54800:17"/> an Oath of him never to diſcover what had paſſed, he gave him two Crowns back, and ſent his ſervants to ſee him out of Town, where they left him; at which <hi>Fortunatus</hi> did not a little rejoyce, foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as he had his dear Companion the Purſe to bear him company, then having abjured ever coming within that Earls Iuriſdiction any more, he departed towards <hi>Brittain;</hi> and after ſome time, came to <hi>Angiers,</hi> a conſiderable City of that Dukedom, where at that time was held a great Feaſt, in Honour of the Marriage of the Dukes Daughter with the Prince of <hi>Saxony;</hi> upon which occaſion a great number of Lords and others, were come thither gallantly attended: upon which, <hi>Fortunatus</hi> notwithſtanding his late bad ſucceſs by deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in horſe fleſh, bought three more horſes and put himſelf in a ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>did Equipage, and likewiſe hired two ſervants, and betook himſelf to the beſt Inn, where he kept company and converſed with the beſt, and ſo continued in great ſplendor till the Celebration of the Marriage.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How an <hi>Iriſh</hi> Gentleman was entertained by <hi>Fortunatus</hi> as his Companion, and what befell them in their Travels.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>WHilſt <hi>Fortunatus</hi> continued at this City, he ſpent moſt part of his time in ſeeing the paſtimes which were made as Pomp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Shows, Maſques, Dauncing, Tilt, Turnament, and many other Noble Exerciſes; and ſo being uſed every day to depart from the Inn with his men, the Hoſt began at laſt to miſtruſt he would give him the ſlip as ſome others had done, and thereupon acquainted him with his thought, at which <hi>Fortunatus</hi> ſmiling, put his hand into his Purſe, and pulled out a hundred Crowns, the which he gave to the Hoſt: ſaying, here honeſt fellow take this, and when thou thinkeſt we have had as much as it comes to ask for more, I ſhall not be very inquiſitive to know the account.</p>
               <p>At this the Hoſt began to look very pleaſant ever after, ſhewing great reſpect to <hi>Fortunatus,</hi> ſetting him at the upper end of the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:54800:18"/> Table, and handing him the choiceſt diſhes of meats, and beſt wine; though ſeveral Noble Perſons eyes were preſent.</p>
               <p>Not long after, as he was ſitting at dinner with ſix Earls and ten Lords, beſides other Gentlemen of good faſhion; ſeveral Muſitianers came and offered to play before them, telling them that they had been Gentlemen, but where now fallen to decay, and were forced to take up that employ for their living; when they had played a good while, an Earl at the Table asked one of them that was more likely than the reſt, what Countryman he was? who replyed that he was an <hi>Iriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> and had ſpent all his Eſtate in traveling; for, ſaid he, I have been in moſt parts of the World, and can name, and have ſeen moſt of the Emperors, Kings, and Soveraign Princes in <hi>Europe, Aſia,</hi> and <hi>Africa;</hi> and can diſcribe the Splendor of their Courts, the manners and cuſtoms of their Countrys, and ſpeak moſt Languages, with many other things.</p>
               <p>Then they asked him his name, who told them he was called <hi>Leo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paldus,</hi> and came of a worſhipful Family, which appeared no leſs in his Carriage and portly Demeanour; upon which the Nobility and Gentry being moved to Compaſſion, that ſo goodly a perſon ſhould be reduced to poverty, they liberally diſtributed Money amongſt him and his Companions, and deſired him to ſtay and attend them whilſt the Feaſt continued; for which, not onely he, but the reſt returned their Honours a thouſand thanks: Then one of the Earls asked him if he would be willing to live with him, and become a Tutor, and he ſhould never want; but he excuſed it, ſaying, He had left a Wife and Children in his own Country, which he much longed to ſee.</p>
               <p>Now <hi>Fortunatus</hi> who had curiouſly obferved the Man, began to think with himſelf, could I but procure him for my Companion in Travel, I ſhould think my ſelf happy; and thereupon when Din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner was ended, he ſent privately for him to come to his Chamber, where when he entred, <hi>Fortunatus</hi> Saluted him after the moſt cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous manner, and told him that he was minded to ſpend the reſidue of his Days in Travel, and that if he would become his Companion, he would ſo provide for him, that he ſhould ever have plenty; as likewiſe provide a Horſe for himſelf, and another for a man who ſhould wait on him.</p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:54800:18"/>
               <p>To this <hi>Leopaldus</hi> replyed, That he could be well content with ſuch a Proffer, if it were not that he ſo much longed to ſee his Wife and Children, which had been the occaſion of his return out of far Countries; to which <hi>Fortunatus</hi> anſwered him, That if he would make him a ſolemn promiſe, that he would afterwards accompany him, he would go with him into <hi>Ireland</hi> firſt, and bear his Charges thither, and then we will return to <hi>Cyprus</hi> the Iſle wherein I was born, and ſo from thence by Sea and Land, travel into other Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries and Kingdoms as thou ſhalt think beſt fit.</p>
               <p>At this <hi>Leopaldus</hi> inwardly rejoyced; but having known the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding Expence of Travel, had thought with himſelf that <hi>Fortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natus</hi> could never be able to perform what he promiſed; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon told him, unleſs he had great Sums of Money, it was in vain to undertake what he propoſed: Let me alone for that, ſaid <hi>Fortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natus,</hi> for I ſhall have Money in all places where I come; If it be ſo, ſaid <hi>Leopaldus,</hi> and thou wilt perform thy promiſe, I am con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent; and thereupon <hi>Leopaldus</hi> having a Horſe provided for him, and another for his Man, which <hi>Fortunatus</hi> cauſed to be hired: af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Hoſt was diſcharged, they departed the City, and ſo viſiting many fair Cities and Towns, at laſt they came to <hi>Bruges</hi> in <hi>Flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> where taking Shipping they came for <hi>London,</hi> where having ſtayed awhile, they departed for <hi>Scotland,</hi> ſtill viſiting all Places of note as they paſſed; and from <hi>Scotland</hi> they Sailed over Sea into <hi>Ireland,</hi> where coming to <hi>Londonderry,</hi> and from thence to <hi>Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drink,</hi> where was his own Houſe, he was not known, by reaſon of the Alteration his long Abſence had made; but finding his Wife and Children all in good Health, he by many Tokens made them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand who he was, to their no ſmall Ioy; the next day came thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Fortunatus</hi> and his Men, who perceiving that <hi>Leopoldus</hi> was but ſlenderly provided, gave him a 100 Crowns, bidding him go and buy ſuch Proviſion as was convenient, and Invite the chief of his Neigbours to Dinner, the which he did, and very ſplendedly En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained them.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>woodcut of monk unlocking door with Fortunatus, Leopoldus, the Abbot and another figure standing behind him; repeated on p. 79</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>repetitive woodcut of multiple trees</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>This made <hi>Fortunatus</hi> the more deſirous to ſee it, and reſting that Night, he got up the next Morning, and having ſhrieved him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and ſayd his Prayers devoutly, he, together with <hi>Leopoldus</hi> who offered to accompany him, went into a Hole behind the Altar, to which there was a Door, and a pair of Stairs of earth; when they were in, the Monks ſhut the Door after them, and prayed for their happy return as they uſed to do for others that had gone in before them, and withal admoniſhed them not to venture too far, leſt they were loſt, as many Pilgrims had been, who were not found again in three or four days.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fortunatus</hi> and <hi>Leopoldus</hi> being in, went forwards about a 100 paces, and coming into a narrow paſſage that they could go but one a breaſt, they turned ſo often, that they at laſt were loſt in the Labyrinth, not knowing when they went backwards or when for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, ſo that they continued wandring too and fro for the ſpace of two days, hearing loud Shrieks and Groans, and now and then felt hot Flaſhes, which ſo amazed them, that they wiſhed they had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ventured in; and beſides Hunger began to aſſault them very grievouſly, inſomuch that <hi>Fortunatus</hi> began to ſay, that now his Purſe was uſeleſs, and that notwithſtanding he had Gold and Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, yet that would not ſatisfie Nature, but that they muſt now ſtarve with Hunger; and thereupon they both fell upon their Knees, and made a Vow, that if God would be pleaſed to deliver them this once, they would never be ſo raſhly venturous again.</p>
               <p>Now the third Day came, and the Servants without being very impatient of their Maſters ſtay, called at the Mouth of the Hole, and held in lighted Torches, but in vain; when as not only they, but the Abbot and Prieſts were in great perplexity, as thinking <hi>Fortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natus</hi> and <hi>Leopoldus</hi> were either loſt or dead; inſomuch that they began to fing Maſs for their Souls, whenas the Abbot calling an old man to mind who had meaſured the Hole with Ropes, he ſent for him, and willed him to go in and ſeek for two Gentlemen that had
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:54800:20"/> loſt themſelveſt therein; the which upon the Servants promiſe, that their Maſters ſhould give him a 100 Crowns, he undertook; ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, if they were alive he would bring them thence: Whereupon ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king with him a lighted Torch, and a Pipe, he entred; but that Torch ſoon went out, yet he paſſed on playing upon his Pipe; and after having gone a thouſand paces, began to hollow to them, who with faint Voices anſwered, till at laſt he being directed by the Sound. came to them, and informed them that he was come to fetch them out; and taking them by the hand, bid them follow him, which they did with no ſmall content; when they came out, they were exceeding feeble, yet greatly rejoyced at their Deliverance: So that when <hi>Fortunatus</hi> his men told him how they had agreed with the old man for a 100 Crowns, he gave him 200, and then ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a ſumptuous Dinner, he Invited the Abbot and the reſt, and deſired them to return God thanks for the great Deliverance he had ſent them, giving 200 Crowns amongſt the Prieſts, and after leave taken, departed; and taking Ship, ſet Sail for <hi>Calice,</hi> and from thence went to <hi>Paris,</hi> and ſo over-land to <hi>Rome,</hi> ſeeing ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Countries, and ſtrange things in their way.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XIII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How <hi>Fortunatus</hi> Travelled from <hi>Rome</hi> to <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> and what befell him at the Coronation of the Emperor.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>FOrtunatus</hi> and <hi>Leopoldus</hi> having continued at <hi>Rome</hi> ſome time, to take notice of the Splendor and Pomp of the Biſhops Court, departed thence for <hi>Venice;</hi> whereupon News had, that the Emperor of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> intended to Crown his Son Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror, by reaſon he was ſo old that he could not Weild the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as he ought,; the State of <hi>Venice</hi> reſolved to ſend an Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſador with ſeveral Preſents to congratulate his Eſtabliſhment in the Empire: And now the Gallies being ready, <hi>Fortunatus</hi> ſo or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred the matter with the Captain of one of them, that he got leave for him and his Retinue to paſs to <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> therein; when
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:54800:20"/> after ten days Sail they came within ſight of the City, and were met by ſome of the Emperors Gallies who were ſent to welcom them; and coming on ſhore, the Amboſſador had a ſtately Houſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided him; but as for <hi>Fortunatus, Leopoldus,</hi> and their Men, they were forced to betake themſelves to an Inn, which proved <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>one of the beſt; for the Hoſt was a Thief, and uſually watched his opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity to rob his Gueſts when they were ſleeping, who dreamed of no ſuch matter; ſo that the Hoſt perceiving <hi>Fortunatus</hi> to have great ſtore of Money, he reſolved to make bold with ſome of it; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in their abſence got into their Chamber through a private Door, and ſearched all about, but found no Money; ſo that he concluded they carried it all about them, and ſo reſolved when they payd again, to watch where they put it.</p>
               <p>A while after <hi>Fortunatus</hi> came to pay, and putting his hand under the Table, pulled out Money, and gave it to <hi>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>poldus</hi> to pay the Reckoning, that it might not be perceived from whence he had it; ſo that the Hoſt marking him well, ſuppoſed it was hidden in his Cloaths, and was reſolved the next Night to put in with him for a ſnack: Now <hi>Fortunatus</hi> in the midſt of his Merriments remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred the time was come wherein he was to perform his Vow made to <hi>Dame Fortune,</hi> about beſtowing <hi>400</hi> Crowns on a Virgin in Marriage; and thereupon he called his Hoſt, and asked him if he knew any honeſt man that had a fair Daughter to beſtow, and he would give her a Portion: the Hoſt told him that a Neighbor of his had one who was marrigable; upon which <hi>Fortunatus</hi> bid the Hoſt go to her Parents, and bid them bring her the next Morning; which the Hoſt neglected to do, ſaying, She was gone abroad, and would not return till late the next Morrow-evening: the which he did, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they ſhould not part with their Money till he had put in for a ſhare; ſo that when they were in Bed, and ſleeping ſoundly by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon they were tired the day before at the noble Paſtimes that were held in the City; about Midnight the Hoſt came through his private Door; and firſt coming to <hi>Leopoldus,</hi> he felt and ſoon found his Purſe, and took from thence <hi>50</hi> Duckets; then coming to <hi>Fortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natus,</hi> he felt his Purſe likewiſe, but not putting his hand into it, he could not perceive any Money; for ſuch was the Secret, that to
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:54800:21"/> all thoſe that felt the out-ſide, it felt empty; whereupon the Hoſt ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving cut it from off his Girdle, threw it under the Bed; and ſo ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting open all the Doors and Windows departed: when about the third Watch <hi>Leopoldus</hi> awaked, and eſpying all the Windows open, called to his Servants, as likewiſe to <hi>Fortunatus,</hi> fearing what had hapned; when the Servants were awakened, he chid them ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly for leaving open the Doors and Windows; but they ſtoutly affirmed, that they ſhut them faſt when they went to Bed: upon which <hi>Leopoldus</hi> feeling for his Purſe, found it gone; and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to <hi>Fortunatus,</hi> told him that he was robbed; <hi>Fortunatus</hi> ſtarting up between ſleep and wake, found his Purſe gone alſo; and thereupon he fell into ſuch extream ſorrow, that he ſwoonded away, which cauſed no ſmall ſtir amongſt the Servants; ſo that the Hoſt who all this while ſtood liſtning, came in, and angerly demanded why they made ſuch ado to trouble the whole Houſe? Whereupon they told him they were robbed; to which he replyed, Like enough ſo, perhaps you have Thieves amongſt your ſelves, and have robbed one another: But when he beheld <hi>Fortunatus</hi> in that condition, he alſo affiſted to bring him to himſelf again, telling them that they ought to have looked to their Doors and Windows at a time when ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Thieves were abroad.</p>
               <p>When <hi>Fortunatus</hi> came to himſelf, he was exceeding ſorrowful; upon which the Hoſt asked him, how much Money he had loſt? Who replyed, not much; but that he had loſt a Purſe with a Bill of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change in it worth <hi>1000</hi> Crowns, though it would do them little or no good that had it; for they could not receive the Money unleſs he gave his diſcharge. Now the Hoſt that knew where the Purſe was become, bid him ſearch about; for, ſaid he, it may be thrown ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where in the Room, for few Thieves care for an empty Purſe: Whereupon <hi>Fortunatus</hi> his Men began to look about very diligently, and at laſt under the Bed eſpyed the Purſe, which they took up, and delivered to their Maſter, who did not a little rejoyce that he had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered it; but fearing leaſt by its being cut from his Girdle, it might have loſt its Vertue, he ſecretly put it under the Bed-cloaths, and then thruſting in his hand, drew out Money as formerly; then he began to rejoyce, and putting on his Cloaths, cauſed a Fire to
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:54800:21"/> be made, and Wine to be brought: when the Morning was far gone, his Horſes being made ready, he rode abroad, and in his way ordred <hi>Leopaldus</hi> and his Servants to ſtay at a Tavern till he went to his Exchequer, and took Moneys thence ſufficient for his purpoſe; ſo that having bought Five new Purſes, he put in one of them <hi>100</hi> Crowns, the which he gave to <hi>Leopoldus</hi> to buy Neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries, and into the reſt <hi>10</hi> Crowns apiece, the which he gave to his Men every one, bidding them be careful of Thieves for the future; then went he and took out <hi>400</hi> Crowns; which he had promiſed to beſtow upon the Maid in Marriage, and ſo returned to his Inn, and willed his Hoſt to go again to the Parents of the Maid; which he did, and finding her likewiſe at home, he told the Father upon what account he came,: How that a Gentleman that lodged at his Inn, deſired him to bring his Daughter thither, and he would do good for her in order to procure her a happy Match: but the old man thinking it was a Trap to get his Daughter thither to Debauch her, would by no means conſent; ſaying, That his Daughters Virginity was all ſhe had to ſet her off in Marriage, and if by any means ſhe ſhould loſe that, ſhe would not only undo her ſelf, but be a ſtain to all her Kindred; and ſaid he, I know there are many ſlip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery Blades abroad, therefore I will not truſt my Daughter from home amongſt them; but if the Gentleman has any good meaning, and intends to ſee my Daughter, let him come to my houſe and he ſhall be welcom, but to let her come to any Gentleman abroad, I will not.</p>
               <p>At this the Hoſt being much diſpleaſed, departed, and told <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunatus</hi> all that had paſſed, endeavouring to incenſe him againſt the Virgin, and to beſtow his Money upon ſome other; but <hi>Fortuna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> very well approving of the Fathers blunt and well-meaning, cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed his Servants to make ready his Horſe, and to attend him thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; the Hoſt being there when they came to the Door, the Hoſt knocked hard, and the good man opening the ſame; he told him, that ſince he refuſed to let his Daughter come to the Gentleman, he was come to her: which the good Woman hearing and perceiving his Splendid Equipage, ſhe run and cauſed the Wench to put on her beſt Cloaths, and prick up her Ears after the beſt manner ſhe
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:54800:22"/> could; and ſo with as much trouble as it is to bring a Bear to the Stake, brought her into the Room where <hi>Fortunatus</hi> was; who taking him to be a Prince at leaſt, fell down on her knees before him, but he gently raiſed her, telling the Father on what account he came; therefore ſaid he, if there be any young-man that is deſerving of her hereabouts, let him come and I will give him a good Portion with her. At which the Mother told him, Yes, there was a Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours Son who loved her intirely, and would have wedded her long ago, had not his Parents reſtrained him, by reaſon her Portion was no ways anſwerable to his: Then <hi>Fortunatus</hi> asked the Maid, if ſhe liked the Youth? to which ſhe replyed, She would be ruled by her Parents, and what they thought fit ſhould be a law with her: Nay, nay, ſays her Mother, and it ſhall pleaſe yout Majeſty, ſhe likes him well enough, and has upon my Faith and Troath a Months mind to him, but that the Bagage is ſhame-fac'd: Then <hi>Fortunatus</hi> order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Youth to be ſent for, and found that they were of a fit age to be coupled; whereupon <hi>Fortunatus</hi> asked him, if he could like to take that Virgin for his Wife, if he would give her a Portion? to which he anſwered, With a very good will, if he would give her any thing conſiderable; for I love her well enough, but dare not marry her without a Portion, leaſt my Friends ſhould diſinherit me: And then he asked the Maid if ſhe was willing, who modeſtly replyed, Yes; then the Friends being had, he ſent for a Prieſt, who having joyned them in Matrimony, he delivered to the young-man a Purſe with <hi>400</hi> Crowns, who with many ſcrapings and cringings received the ſame: He alſo gave Money to the Parents of the Maid to buy them Cloaths, and provide the Wedding-Dinner; for which they gave him a thouſand thanks, and praiſed God that had raiſed them up ſuch a Friend in time of need. Then <hi>Fortunatus</hi> departed to his Inn and went to Dinner; <hi>Leopoldus</hi> and the reſt not a little won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring how he came by ſo much Money.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:54800:22"/>
               <head>CHAP. XIV.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How <hi>Leopoldus</hi> ſlew the Thieviſh Hoſt, and how he and <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunatus</hi> made their Eſcapes afterward.</p>
               </argument>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>repetitive woodcut of single tree</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>woodcut of Fortunatus and Leopoldus in their beds, swords drawn with the host falling next to Leopoldus' bed</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>repetitive woodcut of single tree</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>woodcut of man carrying a body over his shoulder; repeated from p. 12</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>When they were got out of the City, they rod towards <hi>Turky</hi> with all ſpeed, not ſtopping till they had rid about 30 Miles, and then only Baiting a little, they ſet forward again, and were ſo ſwift to avoid purſuit, that they rod 100 Miles that day; the next day they ſet forward again, and came to <hi>Achipania,</hi> a City garriſon'd with <hi>Turks,</hi> and governed by a <hi>Baſhaw;</hi> there they were not fuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to paſs through without a Paſs-port from the Governor, which <hi>Leopoldus</hi> for 24 Crowns obtained: then had they an experienccd Guide alotted them, who had for his Wages a Crown every day; this Guide conducted them to the Great <hi>Turks</hi> Palace, and then, and not till then, could <hi>Fortunatus</hi> be out of fear leſt he ſhould be purſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed:
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:54800:24"/> here they ſtayed a Month to behold the Splendor and Magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence of a Palace which for Riches and ſtately Building ſurpaſſed the Courts of all the Chriſtian Princes, had they been united in one; but ſeeing that they were for the moſt part Heathens, and conſequently God's enemies, they would have no Diſcourſe, nor keep company with any of them: from thence they, croſſing the Country, paſſed through <hi>Bononia, Hungaria, Bohemia, Saxony, Dalmatia, Swevia, Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark,</hi> and many other places, viewing the Monuments and ſtately Buildings as they paſſed, and at laſt went into <hi>Italy;</hi> where paſſing through the Dukedoms of <hi>Millain, Florence, Ferrara, Mantua,</hi> and the Kingdom of <hi>Naples,</hi> they at laſt came to <hi>Venice,</hi> which was then a place for Merchandize, the Richeſt in the World; there he bought many coſtly Iewels, Pearls, Gold Fringe, and Gold Imbroderies, with Velvet and other coſtly Stuff. Now after 16 years abſence, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolving to return into his own Country to viſit his Parents; when he came to <hi>Famogoſta,</hi> he heard they were dead, for which he greatly ſorrowed; and being ſhewed the place of their Burial, he ſtately Monument to be erected, with this <hi>Inſcription;</hi>
                  <q>
                     <l>Under this Marble Pile theſe Victims lie,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe Names Death has not pow'r for to deſtroy;</l>
                     <l>But unto after Ages they ſhall live,</l>
                     <l>And an Example to true Lovers give.</l>
                     <l>Fam'd <hi>Theodorus, Fortunatus</hi>'s Father,</l>
                     <l>And beauteous <hi>Greciana</hi> his dear Mother</l>
                     <l>Lie here Intomb'd, their Bodies here do lie,</l>
                     <l>But their great Souls are wrap'd above the Sky.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>After this he built him a fair Houſe, and entertained ſeveral Maid-ſervants, bought him a Coach and other things neceſſary; ſo that the Gentry began to wonder how he came by ſuch vaſt Sums of Money, when as all of them knew he departed extream poor.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:54800:24"/>
               <head>CHAP. XV.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How <hi>Fortunatus,</hi> by the Kings Command, was married to fair <hi>Caſſandra,</hi> Daughter to the Lord <hi>Nemina.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>WIthin a while after his Arrival in <hi>Cyprus,</hi> he purchaſed the greateſt part of his Fathers Eſtate, which was Sold and Mortgaged; then built he a fair Palace, a Church and Chantry, with Houſes for 12 Prieſts, endowing them with 1400 Crowns a year; made ſtately Parks, Gardens, Fountains, and Fiſh-ponds, with many other rare Devices; Inſomuch that moſt of the Noble-men of <hi>Cyprus</hi> were proud of his Company, and many were very deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to match their Daughters to him: Inſomuch that the King himſelf taking notice of it, and being in diſcourſe with the Lord <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mina,</hi> who had three fair Daughters; he asked him what he thought if <hi>Fortunatus</hi> ſhould requeſt one of his Daughters in marriage? Why truly, replyed he, and it may pleaſe your Majeſty, I do not think it fit, for I perceive he has no great Eſtate, and although he has ready Money, he is ſo prodigal both in Expences and Building, that it cannot laſt long; and therefore I believe your Majeſty would not adviſe me to match any of my Daughters to him, leaſt, as his Father did, he at laſt ſhould come to poverty, notwithſtanding his Riches: Indeed, ſaid the King, he has built a fair Palace, and many other ſtately Edifices, yet his Eſtate is not at all Impaired; for I have been informed that he has Iewels by him worth 100000 Crowns, and yet he will not ſell one of them; therefore if you will take my Advice, offer him one of your Daughters, and I will ſecond the matter.</p>
               <p>By this the Earl perceiving that <hi>Fortunatus</hi> was highly in the Kings Favour, he ſaid, Well, if it pleaſe your Majeſty, I will com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit my Daughters to your diſpoſe, and with whatever your Majeſty ſhall do, I will be well ſatisfied: to which the King anſwered, That ſince he repoſed ſo much truſt in him, he would not only give her in marriage, but give her a Dowry likewiſe; and thereupon ordered the Earl to ſend his three Daughters to the Queen: Whereupon he went
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:54800:25"/> home and acquainted his Wife with what had hapned, with which ſhe ſeemed at firſt diſpleaſed, but after he urged it was the Kings plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, ſhe was contented; and thereupon ſent her three Daughters well attended, and in coſtly Earbs to the Queen, who received them joyfully.</p>
               <p>The King having notice that they were come, he ſent for <hi>Fortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natus,</hi> telling him, that he underſtood he had a deſign to take him a Wife, and that he being loath any of baſe Extraction ſhould poſſeſs ſo fair and coſtly a Building, himſelf would, if he thought fit, provide him One of Noble Birth, and ſuch an One as he doubted not but would pleaſe him: Whereupon <hi>Fortunatus</hi> bowing low, gave his Majeſty many thanks, ſaying, That indeed he intended to ſeek out for a Wife; but ſince his Majeſty had ſo far condeſcended as to give himſelf the trouble of providing him One, he would not look any further, but wholly ſubmit to what his Majeſty thought fit: Then ſaid the King, I have in my Palace three fair Virgins, Daughters to the Lord of <hi>Nemina,</hi> of thoſe you ſhall take your choice; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſay whether you will ſee them ſeparate, or altogether: At this <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunatus</hi> pauſed not, but replyed, If it may pleaſe your Majeſty, I would ſee them together, and hear them ſpeak one after another; that you ſhall, ſaid the King; and thereupon ſent one of his Pages to the Queen, to get the Ladies in a readineſs, for that he was to bring a Gueſt into the Preſence-Chamber; and having notice that they were prepared, he took <hi>Fortunatus</hi> by the hand, who likewiſe deſired that <hi>Leopoldus</hi> might go with him, which the King conſenting to, they went all three together; when being come, the King ſate down and cauſed the Ladies to be brought before him, and placed in order according to their years, the eldeſt being named <hi>Germania,</hi> the next <hi>Marcepia,</hi> and the youngeſt <hi>Caſſandra.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:54800:25"/>
               <head>CHAP. XVI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How <hi>Fortunatus</hi> havjng his choice of the Lord <hi>Nemina</hi>'s three Daughters, choſe the youngeſt, whoſe Name was <hi>Caſſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dra,</hi> to whom he was married in the preſence of the King of <hi>Cyprus.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>THe Ladies being placed in order, the King demanded of the el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt, whether ſhe had rather continue at Court and be one of the Queens Maids of Honour, or with her Father and Mother; to which, with a modeſt Deportment, ſhe anſwered; That may it pleaſe my So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign Lord the King, it is not ſeemly that I ſhould diſpoſe of my ſelf, but rather that I ſubmit to what your Majeſty or my Father ſhall think moſt convenient; then ſaid the King to the next, tell me <hi>Marcenia</hi> which from your heart you love beſt, the Earl your Father, or the Counteſs your Mother: to which ſhe replyed, That is a hard Queſtion, and therefore I muſt humbly beg your Majeſties pardon to excuſe me, if I anſwer not directly to this Point; becauſe I love them both ſo well, I know not how to incline to either hand, and therefore muſt be ſilent as to my report in that Affair; then the King ſaid, <hi>Caſſandra</hi> prithee tell me, ſhould your Father and Mother be here, and ſeveral young Nobles were dancing, and if your Mother ſhould bid you Dance, and your Father forbid the ſame, which would you chooſe to obey: Indeed my Gracious Soveraign, ſaid ſhe, that Oueſtion is unanſwerable, eſpecially upon ſuch ſhort warning, and by one whoſe tender years are not capable of diſcerning things as they are, for ſhould I obey one, I ſhould diſobey the other, and on either hand prove diſobedient.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>woodcut of a split scene: seven people around a table with three others in the balcony; the wedding of Fortunatus</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>repetitive woodcut of single tree</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>After the Celebration of the Marriage, <hi>Fortunatus</hi> and his Bride were joyed by the King, Queen, and Nobles, but the Siſters of <hi>Caſſandra</hi> wept for madneſs that their younger Siſter ſhould be
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:54800:26"/> choſen and they neglected; which <hi>Fortunatus</hi> perceiving, comforted them in the beſt manner, and ſent for his Casket of Iewels which he had purchaſed at <hi>Venice,</hi> and after having preſented the faireſt to the King and Queen; he beſtowed the reſt upon his Bride and her Siſters, as likewiſe upon the Queens Ladys and Maids of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour: he alſo ſent <hi>Leopoldus</hi> with a preſent of 1000 Crowns to the Counteſs of <hi>Nemina,</hi> as alſo to deſire the Earl to repair to Court. The Counteſs when ſhe underſtood he had choſen her youngeſt Daughter, whom ſhe entirely loved, was ſomewhat diſpleaſed, but diſſembling the matter, ſhe and the Earl come to Court in the moſt ſplendid manner they could: and at their arrival were welcomed by the King and Queen, and all the Nobility; as likewiſe by <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunatus,</hi> who beſtowed richer preſents on them than before, which quite diſſolved the Counteſſes diſpleaſure; inſomuch that they thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed God and the King, that they had provided her Daughter ſo brave and rich a Husband, eſpecially when ſhe perceived how highly <hi>Fortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natus</hi> was in the Kings Favour.</p>
               <p>Then ſaid the King; I think it convenient that the Wedding Feaſt be kept in our Pallace; nay, ſaid <hi>Fortunatus,</hi> I beſeech your Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty let it be at my own Houſe in <hi>Famogoſta;</hi> it would content me, ſaid the King, that it ſhould be there, were it not for the exceſſive charge it will put you to; no matter for that, ſaid <hi>Fortunatus,</hi> for there is nothing that can be had in all the <hi>Iſle</hi> of <hi>Cyprus,</hi> but it ſhall be there at your Majeſties ſervice; and if it ſhall pleaſe your Majeſty to ordein Tilts and Turnaments, I ſhall be exceeding glad, that I may prove my ſelf a man before your Majeſty; to all this the King conſented, and ordered his Nobles to be ready within two days, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part for <hi>Famogoſta;</hi> as likewiſe the Ladys that waited upon the Queen, and others: and for that day the Bridegroom and Bride dined privately with the King and Queen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:54800:27"/>
               <head>CHAP. XVII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How <hi>Fortunatus</hi> and his Bride, were accompanied by the King and Queen to <hi>Famogoſta,</hi> and what happened there, during the Wedding Feaſt.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>FOrtunatus</hi> having the Kings conſent to go with him to <hi>Famo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goſta;</hi> ſent <hi>Leopoldus</hi> with 2000 Crowns to buy proviſion for the entertainment, who ſo well managed the matter, that at the Kings arrival all things were in a readineſs; there was he met in the great Court by all manner of Muſitians playing Melodiouſly, and entring the Hall, preſented with Gorgious ſights: brave Dancing and Odoriferous ſmells, Seeling being freſted with Silver Shells, wrought in the Curiouſeſt manner: and the ſides of Cedar, Guilt with Gold; as likewiſe ſeveral Lamps of Silver, burning Spicecy Oyl, that caſt a fragrant ſmell.</p>
               <p>When the Table was ſpread, the King, and all the Nobility won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred at the ſtore, ſaying, that they had not ſeen the like in <hi>Cyprus</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and all that day continued they exceeding merry: but when night came, <hi>Fortunatus</hi> was deſireous to go to Bed with his Bride, for as yet he had not bedded her; whereupon the King, Queen, Lords, and Ladys, accompanied them to their Chamber, and there uſed ſuch Diverſion as is uſual upon the Wedding Night; which made the young Bride bluſh, but they retireing, left her to the imbraces of <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunatus,</hi> who, 'tis to be ſuppoſed, in the like caſe would have been.</p>
               <p>The Feaſt laſted 14 days, and then urgent buſineſs at Court cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the King away, he ſent for <hi>Fortunatus,</hi> as likewiſe the Earl his Father-in-Law, and the Counteſs; and gave them all thanks for his entertainment, but the Counteſs appearing ſomewhat Melancholly, the King asked the cauſe: when as ſhe told him, that ſhe feared her Son-in-Law would ſoon waſte all he had, ſo that her Daughter would be reduced to Poverty; therefore ſhe ſhould not be content unleſs he would ſettle ſome Dower in Land upon her; to which <hi>Fortunatus</hi> replyed, that he confeſſed his Lands were ſmall, but as for ready mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, I will give 8000 Duckates into my Father-in-Laws hands to diſpoſe of as he ſhall think fit, for the good of my Wife; which the
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:54800:27"/> King no ſooner heard, but he told them it was very opportunely hit; for ſaid he, the Earl of <hi>Litgorn</hi> is about to ſell a Lordſhip, with a Caſtle and other Appurtenances, being neceſſitated for ready mony, and if you think good I will ſend for him; to this they all agreed, and when the Earl was come, the King acquainted him with the matter: upon which to the great content of all parties, a bargain was driven, the Earl of <hi>Litgorn</hi> in lieu of 7000 Duckets deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up his Title to the ſaid Lordſhip, with the Government of the Village to <hi>Fortunatus,</hi> who delivered the Charge thereof to his Father-in-law for the uſe of <hi>Caſſandra,</hi> which pleaſed the Counteſs beyond meaſure.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XVIII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How after the Departure of the King, Queen and Nobility, <hi>Fortunatus</hi> ordained a Feaſt for all the chief Citizens.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>DVring the Kings ſtay, <hi>Fortunatus</hi> ſet up three Iewels of great price, the firſt the Nobility Tilted for, he that did beſt being to poſſeſs the ſame; the ſecond was provided for the Eſquires and Gentlemen; the third for the Citizens, Yeomen and Servants, which cauſed them to Iuſt for nine days; which Paſtime exceedingly pleaſed the King and all preſent. Now the time came that at the end of Fourteen days, the King and Queen with the reſt of the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility would depart, <hi>Fortunatus</hi> with all his Attendants accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied them Ten Miles outward of their way, and then the King de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring him to return, he came back to his Bride, and calling his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants together, gave order that within two days they ſhould provide another Feaſt for the Citizens and Gentlemen thereabouts; which was accordingly done, it holding Four days with great plenty of Mirth.</p>
               <p>The Feaſt ended, <hi>Fortunatus</hi> taking <hi>Leopoldus</hi> aſide, ſaid; For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſmuch as thou haſt faithfully ſerved me hitherto, I will now propoſe to thee three Things, take thy choice of either: Firſt, if thou art minded to return into <hi>Ireland,</hi> I will give thee four Servants to
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:54800:28"/> attend thee, and as much Money as ſhall maintain thee during life. Secondly, If thou wilt live in the Houſe with me (for I am not now mindful of Travel) I will maintain thee to thy hearts content. Thirdly, If it ſhall otherways like thee, I will give thee a Horſe in this City, and maintain Servants to wait upon thee, and thou ſhalt lack nothing during life: For theſe kind Offers <hi>Leopoldus</hi> greatly thanked him, ſaying, he was unworthy of them; As for the firſt, I being now ſpent with Age and Travel, by reaſon of the tediouſneſs of the way, ſhall hardly get thither; and for the ſecond, ſeeing you have a fair Lady to accompany you, and many Servants, my being in the Houſe will be needleſs; therefore if it ſhall ſo pleaſe you, I will imbrace the latter: with which <hi>Fortunatus</hi> was content, and bought him a Horſe provided him Servants, and all Neceſſaries, allowing him 20 Duckets a week: Then <hi>Leopoldus</hi> prayed that he might be ſtill of his Councel in all weighty Affairs, and that he would not ſuffer his love towards him to decay, which he ſolemnly ſwore to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve. In awhile after, <hi>Leopoldus</hi> ſent into <hi>Ireland</hi> for his Wife and Children, acquainting them by Letters of the proſperous Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion he was in, and wiſhed them to ſell off what they had and come to him; but before their arrival, he, by reaſon of a grievous ſickneſs, died, to the great grief of <hi>Fortunatus</hi> and his Lady, who cauſed him to be buried in a fair Tomb in the <hi>Chancel</hi> of the Church which he had built,: and upon the arrival of <hi>Leopoldus</hi> his Wife and Children, he entertained them courteouſly, comforting them in the beſt manner, and placing them in the houſe he had given to <hi>Leopoldus,</hi> and there maintaining them ſo long as they lived.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XIX.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How fair <hi>Caſſandra</hi> was brought to Bed of two fair Sons, whom <hi>Fortunatus</hi> cauſed to be Baptized, naming the elder <hi>Ampedo,</hi> and the younger <hi>Andolocia.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>NOw <hi>Fortunatus</hi> being in the height of Ioy, daſly ſolacing with his fair Bride the beautiful <hi>Caſſandra,</hi> he wanted nothing but
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:54800:28"/> Children, the deareſt Pledges of mutual Love, for which he often pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and cau ed the Prieſts to pray; till at laſt God heard him, and the tender Bride grew big with her fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt Son, which afterwards was Chriſt'ned with great Solemnity, and called <hi>Ampedo;</hi> ſcare had they made an end of rejoycing for this Son before the teeming Lady perceived her ſelf quick with another Child, which proved a Son alſo, and was named <hi>Andolocia;</hi> this brought a double Ioy, and the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, becauſe <hi>Fortunatus</hi> remembred the words of Dame <hi>Fortune,</hi> which were, That if he had no Iſſue, the Vertue of his Purſe ſhould fail with his Life: but <hi>Caſſandra</hi> knew not of this nor of the Purſe; <hi>Fortunatus</hi> not thinking it convenient to truſt a Woman with ſo weighty a Secret. After they came to years of Maturity, he cauſed them to be brought up in Learning, providing for them the ableſt Tutors he could get; as likewiſe to Fence, Iuſt, play upon Muſick, and all other Arts and Sciences that belonged to a compleat. Gentleman, for theſe were all the Children he was likely to have by the fair <hi>Caſſandra.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XX.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How <hi>Fortunatus</hi> prevailed with his Wife to Travel again, and what befel him during his being abroad.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>WHen <hi>Fortunatus</hi> had lived with his Wife about ſixteen years, he began to think of his former Travels, conſidering that for the moſt part they had been in <hi>Europe;</hi> whereupon he had been deprived of ſeeing ſuch ſtrange Rarities as other Countries in <hi>Aſia</hi> did pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce, he thereupon reſolved to travel once again, but durſt not for a long time diſcloſe his Mind to his Wife, for fear of driving her into a Fit of Melancholy; but at laſt as he was walking with her in the Garden, he began to diſcourſe her about his former Travels, and at laſt told her, that ſeeing it was not likely that he ſhould have any more Children, he was purpoſed to ſee the <hi>Indies, Egypt,</hi> and <hi>Paleſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> for that he had already travelled over one half of the World. This drew Tears from the fair <hi>Caſſandra,</hi> who with tender weeping and
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:54800:29"/> many Intreaties beſought him out of love to her and her Children, and by all the mutual Ties of their Conjugal Love, not to leave her: for in his abſence her life would be altogether comfortleſs: Then he comforted her, telling her, he would make but a ſhort ſtay of it, reck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oning to return within a year; but this nothing pacified the diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolate Lady, who demanded of him in what ſhe had offended, that he who was the Ioy of her Life, would leave her? and that if ſhe had tranſgreſſed in ought, ſhe would double her Obedience for the future: To which he anſwered, that ſhe never offended him, but that he lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved her as dear as his life, yet he was reſolved to go, and nothing but Sickneſs or Death ſhould hinder him; then ſhe deſired him if he would needs go, that he ſhould travel into a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Country, and not expoſe his life to the Cruelty of <hi>Heathens,</hi> who moſt of all envy <hi>Chriſtians</hi> and ſeek their blood; to which he replyed, That he had ſeen all the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Countries already, and that now he reſolved to ſee both the <hi>Indies,</hi> and the places he had before named: But when ſhe perceived ſhe could not prevail with him neither by Tears nor Intrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, ſhe fell down in a Swound, which moved <hi>Fortunatus</hi> to Compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; when coming to her ſelf, ſhe ſighed bitterly, ſaying, O what have I done that I muſt loſe the Ioy of my Life ſo ſoon? Then ſhe ſent to her Father and Mother to come and intreat him to ſtay, but they prevailed not: So that when ſhe ſaw there was no way to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail, and that he had made a Vow to depart, ſhe began a little to be contented, and upon his promiſe of a quick return, unwillingly yield<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; when as <hi>Fortunatus</hi> leaving her 10000. Crowns, he promiſes himſelf a Ship, and with his Purſe went on Board only accompanied with two Servants.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How <hi>Fortunatus</hi> ſet Sail from <hi>Cyprus,</hi> and travelled into many ſtrange Countries, and of the Adventures he met withal.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>FOrtunatus</hi> having hired many skilful Mariners, he commanded to looſe their Anchor and Sail for <hi>Alexandria,</hi> a City in <hi>Egypt,</hi>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:54800:29"/> where in ſhort time having a proſperous Wind they arrived; when coming into the Port, the <hi>Soldan</hi>'s Officers demanded who was Maſter of the Ship? To which the Mariners anſwered, one <hi>Fortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natus</hi> a Noble-man of the Iſſe of <hi>Cyprus;</hi> then they ſaid, he muſt appear before the <hi>Soldan,</hi> and make his Preſent, which was the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom of them that came into that Port: <hi>Fortunatus</hi> hearing this, took with him ſeveral rich Iewels, and ſo went to the <hi>Soldan</hi>'s Court; being conducted thither by the Guards that uſually wait upon the Sea-Coaſt on the like occaſion, where when he was arrived, he ord'red them to ſet a fair Table; which being done accordingly, he ſet many fair Iewels thereon, but had ſcarce time to place them before the <hi>Soldan</hi> came attended with his Nobles, and a great Guard, and perceiving the Iewels, he ſuppoſed they were ſet for Sale; and thereupon began to inquire their Price; upon which <hi>Fortunatus</hi> demanded whether he liked them? to which the <hi>Soldan</hi> replyed, Very well; foraſmuch as they were the faireſt that he had ſeen: then ſaid <hi>Fortunatus,</hi> they are at your Highneſs's Service, take them and diſpoſe of them as you pleaſe: When the <hi>Soldan</hi> heard him ſay ſo, he marvelled greatly that one Merchant ſhould make a Preſent richer than any Twenty had formerly done, the Iewels not being eſteemed leſs worth than 5000 Crowns; yet he accepted them, and promiſed <hi>Fortunatus</hi> that they ſhould not be given in vain: and was as good as his word, for he ſent him the next day three Carts laden with Pepper; this did not a little grieve the Merchants, who ſaid amongſt themſelves, we have made many Preſents to the <hi>Soldan,</hi> but never received any return, but we perceive this upſtart Merchant is greatly favoured.</p>
               <p>Within awhile after the <hi>Soldan</hi> ſent to Invite <hi>Fortunatus</hi> to Dinner, providing a very coſtly Entertainment, and in a while after the Lord High Admiral invited him likewiſe, which greatly offended the Merchants, foraſmuch as they had given him great Summs of Money to turn <hi>Fortunatus</hi> out of Favour with the <hi>Soldan;</hi> but <hi>Fortunatus</hi> being thereof advertiſed, out-gave them, ſo that he ever had the Admiral on his ſide: ſo that he had the firſt choice of the rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Merchandize which he ever bought. But now the time being come for the Ships departure, he gave the Maſter of her order to go to <hi>Spain, Holland, England,</hi> and other places, and unlade the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandize,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:54800:30"/> which for the mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t part conſiſted of Spices; and at the end, of one year, to return to <hi>Alexandria</hi> again, where he intended to be: but in the mean while he would travel into many Countries, and if they found him not there, then they ſhould conclude him dead, and carry back the Ship and Goods to <hi>Cyprus,</hi> and there deliver them up to the uſe of his Wife and Children: this they promiſed to do, and thereupon they departed the Maſter to ſteer his Courſe, and <hi>Fortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natus</hi> to Travel.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How <hi>Fortunatus</hi> took his leave of the <hi>Soldan,</hi> and departed for <hi>India,</hi> and how he ſped there.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>FOrtunatus</hi> having procured Letters from the <hi>Soldan</hi> to many Kings and Princes, through whoſe Countries he intended to tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel, he departed with them joyfully, and taking Ship, he ſailed into <hi>Perſia,</hi> where after he had beheld the Splendor of the Emperors Court, he departed to <hi>Cathia,</hi> where the <hi>Cham</hi> of <hi>Tartaria</hi> bears Rule there; he likewiſe ſtaied not long, by reaſon of the Barbarity of the People, who uſe Strangers very rudely; from thence he went through many Deſarts full of wild Beaſts, which put him oft in peril of his life, eſpecially a Tyger which lay in ambuſh behind a Tree, waiting for ſome Traveller; who as ſoon as ſhe eſpied <hi>Fortunatus</hi> coming, ſhe ſet up ſuch a Yelp as made the Foreſt tremble; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon came at him with an open Mouth, ſtretching out her dreadful Paws to graſp him to her, which <hi>Fortunatus</hi> perceiving, he drew his Sword and ſtood upon his Guard, as alſo did his Men: and as the Tyger made at him, <hi>Fortunatus</hi> with a full blow ſmote off one of her fore-legs, which yet inraged her the more, ſo that ſhe came at him again, when he watching his opportunity, thruſt his Sword down her Throat; and ſo reaching her Heart ſhe fell down dead; then he exceedingly rejoyced, and travell'd on; where by the way he found the Remains of dead mens Carkaſſes which had been torn to pieces by the wild Beaſts, and cauſed his Servants to cover them with earth;
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:54800:30"/> this Foreſt was exceeding long, and therefore although they travelled Day and Night, it was two Days and two Nights ere they could paſs it; then riding through many Cities, they came into <hi>India,</hi> or the Country of <hi>Peſter John,</hi> who is Almighty Monarch, and has under him 62 Kings, being Lord of 30 Iſlands, beſides what he poſſeſſes on the Continent or main Land. Here <hi>Fortunatus</hi> met with an old Hermit who was travelling to the <hi>Holy Land,</hi> and gave him 10 Crowns to bear his Charges; this Hermit conducted him and his men the neareſt way to the Court of the Emperor, and gave them an account of the Cuſtoms of the Country, ſaying, That he had paſſed it many times, and that in his youth he had been a great Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veller: then <hi>Fortunatus</hi> requeſted him to accompany him in his Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vels, but he refuſed, ſaying, He was under a Vow to depart ſtraight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways to the <hi>Holy Land,</hi> and ſo giving <hi>Fortunatus</hi> many thanks for his courteous Benevolence, he departed on his way, and <hi>Fortunatus</hi> rode to the Emperors Palace.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXIII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How <hi>Fortunatus</hi> arrived at <hi>Preſter John</hi>'s Court, and was ſpeedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly entertained, and how he met there with two Conjurers, and how they ſent two Witches to ſteal away his Purſe, with many other ſtrange Adventures.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>WHen <hi>Fortunatus</hi> from the top of an Hill beheld the Palace which glittered with Gold, ſo that by reaſon of the reflection of the Sun-beams it ſhone like a Comet, he greatly admired it, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, That ſince it was ſo fair without, it muſt needs be very beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful within, and ſo by Noon he approached it; at which tune the Emperor and his Lords were returned from hunting of wild Beaſts, whereupon he had the opportunity of ſeeing them clad in warlike Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biliments, which was after ſo ſtrange a manner, that he greatly won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d'red; when they were all entred, he came to the Porter, and demand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed if he and his Companions might not be admitted to behold the Palace, and take a view of the Emperor's Magnificent Entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:54800:31"/> that ſo they might report it to his Praiſe, when they returned into their own Country: The Porter perceiving that they were Gentlemen and Strangers, freely admitted them; upon which <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunatus</hi> gave him a Ruby worth 30 Crowns: then coming into the Emperor's Preſence, he ſignified to him, thet he had ſome Preſents for him, and thereupon drew forth his Iewels, which were very rich, for he always bought the faireſt; which the Emperor accepting of, gave him many thanks, and ord'red his chief Officer to feaſt them no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, and to ſhew them all the Riches of his Palace, which were ſuch as <hi>Fortunatus</hi> had never ſeen before; for the Walls ſome were pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with Silver, wherein were ingraven Stories of Knights and Battels, with the valiant Atchievements of the former Emperors; others were hung with Panthars Skins, which caſt a fragrant ſmell; the Pillars that ſupported the Hall they were of Cedar over-laid with Gold, and imboſſed with precious Stones: This pleaſed <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunatus</hi> ſo well, that he gave the Officer a Iewel worth 100 Duckets. Now when Dinner-time was come, <hi>Fortunatus</hi> and his Men were ſet down with the chief Officers and Noble-men; for ſuch is the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom of the Country, that none but the Princes of the Blood may Dine with the Emperor: Now in the midſt of their Mirth, <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunatus</hi> perceived the Bottles and Flagons begin to dance upon the Table, at which he began greatly to wonder; when one that ſate by him whiſper'd him in the Ear, and told him it was done by Magick, and that the Emperor kept two <hi>Necromancers</hi> to make Paſtime for Strangers; now after the Bottles had done dancing, there ſprung up a Tree full of fair Oranges, which ſeveral Blacks came and plucked off, and then the Tree vaniſhed; after that a large Stag came running in, and after him a Pack of Hounds at full Cry, who taking a Courſe or two round the Hall vaniſhed; then ſeveral fair Women in ſtrange Attire came in playing upon Lutes, and after having danced a turn or two, vaniſhed: At this <hi>Fortunatus</hi> was greatly amazed, but well conſidering with himſelf it was only a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſion of the Devil, and no real Subſtance, he reſted the better con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent: Now when Dinner was ended, the Emperor ſent for <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunatus</hi> to ride a Hunting with him, which he gladly did, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into a Foreſt about ſix Miles from the Palace, there they rouzed
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:54800:31"/> a Lyon who was ſleeping in the Thicket, who ſhaked his brindled Mane, and reared ſo loud, that all the Foreſt trembled; upon which the Dogs were uncoupled, of which he roar ſeveral in pieces, and fought againſt ſeveral of them for the ſpace of an Hour; when the <hi>Indians</hi> came running with their Lances, and run him into the body, ſo that he fell down dead, then took they off his Skin as a Trophy of Victory: After that the Dogs found out a great wild Boar, upon which they faſtned, notwithſtanding he gored many of them with his horrid Tusks, which were at leaſt a foot long, &amp; then the Iavelings be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing darted thick at him, he at laſt was killed, and his Head being cut off, was carried before the Emperor upon a Spear, as likewiſe the Lyon's Skin.</p>
               <p>By this time Sun was ſet, which made the Emperor haſten to his Palace, where, at Supper-time, <hi>Fortunatus</hi> drew a great deal of Gold out of his Purſe, and gave amongſt ſuch as attended at the Table, which the <hi>Necromancers</hi> perceiving, who were alſo ſitting at the Table, they thought with themſelves this Stranger muſt needs be exceeding Rich, that can thus liberally diſpence with his Money, therefore it will not be amiſs when he is in Bed, if we uſe our Art, to get ſome of him; ſo that when all was done, and every one gone to their Chambers, they began to mutter over their Charms, and by that means raiſed their Familiars, commandig them to tell them who the Stranger was, and how he came by ſuch quantities of Gold and Iewels; to which they replyed, He was a Merchant of <hi>Cyprus,</hi> and that he had a ſecret Mine which they were forbidden to reveal, which could not be emptied during his Life, and thereupon they vaniſhed: Now the Conjurers ſent for their Wives, who had familiar Spirits likewiſe, to attend them, and could tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form themſelves, to appearance, into any ſhape: they being come, the Conjurers commanded them, in the ſhapes of Monkeys, to enter <hi>Fortunatus</hi> his Lodgings, and bring thence what Treaſure they could find; the which they readily obeyed: when opening the Caſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, they entred; but by clapping them to and again, <hi>Fortunatus</hi> awoke, and ſuppoſing that they had been Thieves, drew his Sword, and ſtriking at a venture, cut one of their Fore-feet off, whereupon they got out at the Window again, making ſuch a lamentable Noiſe
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:54800:32"/> as wakened a great many of thoſe that lodged near, next morning <hi>Fortunatus</hi> getting up, eſpyed a hand lying on the ground, at which he was ſore diſmaid: but as he went to take it up, it was ſnatched from him he knew not how, ſo that he never ſaw it after: yet ſo it happened, that the next day one of the Conjurers Wives had loſt her hand, which accoſioned her Husband to fall out with his fellow, for putting her upon that exploit; inſomuch that falling to Words, they both vowed revenge one of the other, when as he that had his Wife hurt, taking his opportunity when the other was leaning out at a window, he fixed a great pair of Stags Horns upon his head, ſo that he could by no means draw it in, but was obliged to ſtay there till the Charm was diſſolved, which cauſed great laughter to ſuch as beheld it, but in him it cauſed a deſperate reſolve of revenge: ſo that one day he having drawn the Figure of a Man upon the Wall with ſmall cole, he compelled his adverſary, notwithſtanding all the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treagues he uſed to ſtand up againſt it, when immediately the Wall opened, and he ſinking into it, was never heard of afterward.</p>
               <p>Theſe Projects, and Helliſh arts ſo affrighted <hi>Fortunatus,</hi> that he having got together abundance of Merchandize, and the Emperor's Letter of free Traffick in ſuch Countrys as he came into, under the Emperor's Iuriſdiction; he took his leave and departed, travelling towards <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> where he no ſooner arrived, but he found an old <hi>Hermet,</hi> who ſhewed him the Holy Sepulchre, the pieces of the Croſs, the Apoſtle, St. <hi>James</hi>'s Tomb, and many other Relicks, which Pilgrims go thither to ſee; when he had viewed as much as he thought fit, he began to remember the promiſe he had made to his wife, and thereupon taking leave of the Old Man, he journyed to <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dria.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXIV.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How <hi>Fortunatus</hi> was well-comed by the <hi>Souldan,</hi> as he return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to <hi>Alexandria,</hi> and what befell him, during his ſtay.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>FOrtunatus</hi> being now within eight miles of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> he ſent one of his ſervants to acquaint the Admiral of his approach, and
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:54800:32"/> to deſire the <hi>Souldan's</hi> Letters to enter the City with his <hi>Camels,</hi> of which he had about 20 loaden with the riches of <hi>India,</hi> having hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Natives of the Country to drive them, and to have the ſtronger guard, for fear of robbers: when the ſervant had done his helliſh meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, the Admiral ordered his Horſes to be made ready, and rode to meet <hi>Fortunatus,</hi> who lovingly embraced him, and asked him how he had faired, during his travelling in ſtrange Countrys; whereupon <hi>Fortunatus</hi> told him all that had happened from time to time: then he conducted him to the <hi>Souldan,</hi> who was glad of his return, and cauſed a Feaſt to be made for him; when within three days after his coming thither, his Ship arrived from <hi>Famogoſta,</hi> with Letters from <hi>Caſſandra,</hi> who earneſtly deſired his return; ſo that having put his Merchandize on board, he would have ſet Sail: but going to take his leave of the <hi>Souldian,</hi> and to make him a preſent, he would needs have him ſtay and dine with him, which he could not deny him; yet he ſent one of his ſervants to the maſter of the Ship, to require him to be in a readineſs to ſet Sail; for that he intended as ſoon as he had dined, to come on board: the maſter was obedient. and put off the Veſſel, ready to Sail, all her Anchors being weighed; yet the time of <hi>Fortunatus</hi> his coming was prolonged, by reaſon that the <hi>Souldan</hi> held him in diſcourſe about his late travels: the which <hi>Fortunatus</hi> was obliged to relate, thanking the <hi>Souldan</hi> for his Letters, by which means he told him he had found kind Reception in many places, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially from the neighbouring Princes, who ſpeak very well of him. Then would <hi>Fortunatus</hi> have taken his leave, but the <hi>Souldan</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed with him to ſtay ſupper alſo.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="chapter">
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:54800:33"/>
               <head>CHAP. XXV.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How <hi>Fortunatus</hi> going with the <hi>Souldan</hi> into his Treaſury to ſee his Jewels, underſtood the ſecret vertue of his wiſhing Hat, and how wiſhing himſelf on Ship-board, was he brought thither through the Ayr, and ſet Sail for <hi>Cyprus,</hi> with the wiſhing Hat.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>FOrtunatus</hi> being impatient of delay, leaſt he ſhould break his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe with his Wife; after ſupper was ended, he drew out a great deal of Gold, and beſtowed it freely upon the ſervants, and again demanded leave to depart: but the <hi>Souldan</hi> ſeeing his infinite riches, thought that unleſs he ſhewed him his, he might boaſt in his own Country that he had the greater wealth: whereupon he deſired him to follow him; and ſo led him into his Treaſury which was all hung with Cloath of Tinſe, and the Tables ſpread with Iewels, Rings, and Veſſels of Gold and Silver, Gold Chains, and huge Pearls, with many other things of great price, which <hi>Fortunatus</hi> had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſeen the like before: then he had him into another Room, where he ſhewed him on infinite maſs of mony; and now, ſays he, I have one thing more that I eſteem above all that you have yet beheld, this made <hi>Fortunatus</hi> wonder: for, thought he, it muſt be of an ineſteemable price if it exceed what I have ſeen already, and thereupon he grew impatient to have a view of it: when as the <hi>Souldian</hi> taking him by the hand, led him into another Chamber; and there taking down an old hat, ſaid, this is the Iewel; at which <hi>Fortunatus</hi> ſmiled, telling him that was an old hat, and might be bought for a ſmall matter: yes, ſaid the <hi>Souldian,</hi> if it was only a hat, it was of no value, but there is ſuch a ſecret retained in it, that for all the hats in the World, I would not leave it; nay, ſhould I looſe all my Iewels, I could purchaſe more, but ſhould I looſe this hat, ſuch another the World affords not: then was <hi>Fortunatus</hi> very deſireous to know the ſecret it retained; then ſaid the <hi>Souldan;</hi> ſince you are my friend, I will impart it to you; which is this, that having this hat on, where ever you wiſh your ſelf to be, thither ſhall you be conveyed almoſt as ſwift as can be
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:54800:33"/> thought: ſo that when my Nobles are gone a Hunting, it is but wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my ſelf with them, and I am there: when my armies are abroad, I can be with them, and in my Pallace almoſt in a moment; as like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe upon any occaſion, 'tis but putting this hat on, and I can be carryed into any Country with a wiſh, and ſo back again.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>woodcut of Fortunatus sitting in the window with the sultan standing, arms in the air</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>repetitive woodcut of multiple trees</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>The <hi>Soldan</hi> being greatly perplexed in his mind for the loſs of his Hat, was reſolved to aſend after <hi>Fortunatus</hi> into <hi>Cyprus;</hi> there to make him large offers, if he would either ſend or bring it; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon he ſent for <hi>Marcholandus</hi> a <hi>Venetian,</hi> that ſerved under him, and acquainted him with what had paſſed, and willed him to take one of his beſt Ships, and follow <hi>Fortunatus</hi> into <hi>Cyprus;</hi> and firſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade him by intreaty and promiſes to reſtore the Hat, and if that would not do, to complain of his Treachery to the King of the <hi>Iſland,</hi> and if he refuſed to do Iuſtice, to denounce a War againſt him; this the <hi>Venetian</hi> gladly undertook, as well knowing, if he could recover the Hat, the <hi>Soldan</hi> would greatly favour and reward him; and ſo having all things in a readineſs, he ſet Sail.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXVI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How the <hi>Soldan's</hi> Ambaſſador came after <hi>Fortunatus</hi> to <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prus,</hi> for the Wiſhing Hat, and how he complained to the King; but was ſent away without it.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>FOrtunatus</hi> after two months departure from <hi>Alexandria,</hi> arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved at <hi>Cyprus,</hi> where he was joyfully met by a great number of Nobility, and conducted to the Kings preſence; who welcomed him home, and asked him of his travels, the which he at large related, and then taking his leave, put on his Wiſhing Hat, and going without the City, wiſhed himſelf at his own Houſe, and was there in a trice: when coming in, he met <hi>Caſſandra,</hi> who run to him, and claſping him in her arms, could not ſpeak to him a good while for joy; then he ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:54800:34"/> ſaluted his Sons and Servants, he commanded meat to be ſet before him; and the next day invited a great number of his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours to dine with him, whom he feaſted after the beſt manner.</p>
               <p>Now when he had been at home about eight days, on the 10th of his arrival in the Iſland, <hi>Marcholandus,</hi> who was ſent by the <hi>Sold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi> came to his Houſe, and deſired to ſpeak with him; who coming to him, he deſired that they might be in private: whereupon <hi>Fortunatus</hi> took him by the hand, and led him into the Dining Room, and then willed him to declared his buſineſs; whereupon he delivered him the <hi>Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dans</hi> Letter, and therewithal informed him how ungreatful he had been, in taking away the Hat, yet the <hi>Soldan</hi> would forget it all, and highly reward him, if he would reſtore it; I muſt confeſs, ſaid <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunatus,</hi> the <hi>Soldan</hi> has cauſe to be offended, but let him thank his own folly in putting it upon my Head, I knew not the vertue of it before he declared it; and therefore ſince I ran the hazard of drowning, by flying on Ship-board with it, I am in the mind never to part with it. Then <hi>Marcholandus</hi> told him what offers the <hi>Soldan</hi> had made him, if he would reſtore it: and therefore out of all love deſired him to let him carry it with him, or that he would carry it himſelf; but <hi>Fortunatus</hi> told him he would not part with it for the <hi>Soldan's</hi> Kingdom, and therefore willed him to ceaſe his ſuit.</p>
               <p>Vpon this, <hi>Marcholandus</hi> growing impatient, began to threaten him; ſaying, that he would complain to the King, and if no redreſs could be had there, the <hi>Soldan</hi> would right him by Arms: at which <hi>Fortunatus</hi> ſmiling, bid him do as he pleaſed, and thereupon <hi>Marcho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landus</hi> departed to the Court, where procuring to be admitted to the King's preſence, he grievouſly complained of <hi>Fortunatts;</hi> telling all that had happened concerning the Hat, and deſired his Maieſty to uſe his Prerogative Royal, in compelling him to reſtore it; but the King ſaid that <hi>Fortunatus</hi> was his dear friend, and he would not in any wiſe uſe compulſion towards him; but if he would deliver it up of his own accord well and good, but if not, the Law was open, and he muſt take his Regular Courſe. But <hi>Marcholandus</hi> well knew that <hi>Fortunatus</hi> was too powerfull in his own Country, for a ſtranger to wage Law againſt him: whereupon he told the King, that upon the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſal of delivering the Hat, he had a Commiſſion to denounce War, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:54800:35"/> as you pleaſe for that, ſaid the King; and tell the <hi>Soldan,</hi> that although I eſteem his friendſhip, yet I fear not his anger, but ſhall defend my ſelf as well as I can; upon this, <hi>Morcholandus</hi> return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed very heavy, and told the <hi>Soldian</hi> all that had paſſed, who thereupon conceived ſuch an inward grief for the loſs of his Hat, that in a ſhort time he dyed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXVII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How <hi>Fortunatus</hi> finding himſelf in a declining condition, prepared himſelf for another World.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>FOrtunatus</hi> being now about 60 years of Age, began to bethink himſelf that his thread of Life was almoſt at an end, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon he reſolved to prepare himſelf for a future ſtate, greatly lament<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the loſs of ſo much precious time as he had ſpent in frivilous and vain trifles, wiſhing that he had choſen wiſdom rather than riches; for, ſaid he, they are ever cumberſome, troubleſome, and full of danger: how often have they deſtroyed both Soul and Body, and what wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is there in the World that will not be done for mony? What hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid Bloodſhed, Maſſacres, and Civil Wars, does it ſtir up? Well! I muſt confeſs, for the greateſt part of my Life, I have had exceeding plenty, but have not lived ſo free and truly merry, as when I had no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but what I worked for: how often has my life been endanger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by reaſon of my Purſe? nay, paſt doubt I had been murthered long ſince, for if it; any had known its vertue; but now I will earneſtly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent me of my former folly; and upon that he let fall many tears: at which inſtant, <hi>Caſſandra</hi> coming in, demanded the cauſe of his hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vineſs, to whom he imparted it without any diſſimulation; and ſhe on the other hand ſtrove to comfort him: but at laſt his Melancholly drew him into a Conſumption, which ſoon occaſioned his Death, as ſhall in the next Chapter be ſhown.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="chapter">
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:54800:35"/>
               <head>CHAP. XXVIII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How <hi>Fortunatus</hi> falling ſick, made his Will; and declared to his Sons the virtue of his Purſe and the Hat, with a Comm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>and not to diſcloſe them to any, as likewiſe of his Death.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>FOrtunatus</hi> being ſick unto death, and perceiving his end to be nigh, called his Sons to him and bleſſed them, biding them to live lovingly and peaceably together: and that he would leave them a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient Competency to maintain them both in a moſt ſplendid conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; but, ſaid he, it is ſuch a ſecret, as will looſe its vertue if once diſcovered, therefore take my Counſel in all points, and ſo you will proſper, or otherwiſe be in perpetual danger, for ſeldom is it ſeen, that diſobedient Children proſper: when he had ſaid thus much, he called for his Purſe and Hat and advertiſed them of the ſecrets they contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſaying, that no Mortal ever yet knew the vertue of the Purſe, but himſelf excepted: but as for the Hat, ſaid he, I got it from the <hi>Soldan</hi> of <hi>Babylon,</hi> who offered me many rich preſents for to have it again, he
<figure>
                     <figDesc>repetitive woodcut of single tree</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>woodcut of Fortunatus in bed with two men standing next to the bed</figDesc>
                  </figure> eſteeming it more worth, than all his ineſtimable Treaſure, therefore as you tender the enjoying of them, do not in any wiſe diſcloſe the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret virtue of either of them, leſt in ſo doing, you either looſe them or
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:54800:36"/> your lives; and farther, he adviſed them not to part the Iewels, but to live together lovingly, and when he had ſo ſaid, he cryed with a loud voice! Lord receive my Spirit, and ſo yielded up the Ghoſt: after which, his Sons and his Wife made great Lamentation for him; and cauſed him to be buried in the Chancel, near his Father and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in a new Tomb, which he had cauſed to be built in his life<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time.</p>
               <p>About a month after, <hi>Caſſandra,</hi> for the exceeding ſorrow ſhe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived at his Death, fell into a violent Feavour, and dyed likewiſe: and was, by her Sons, buried in the ſame Sepulcher with her Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band. Now after the days of Mourning were over, <hi>Andolocia, Fortunatus</hi> his youngeſt Son, being inflamed with a deſire to Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel; upon reading what adventures his Father had met with in ſtrange Countrys, he thus beſpeak to his Brother. Dear, Brother, ſince we are both in our Youth and Strength, 'tis not fit that we ſhould ſpend our time in idleneſs, therefore let us travel, and ſee ſtrange Countries; but this nothing liked <hi>Ampedo,</hi> the Eldeſt, who was given rather to the reſt of a quiet Life; whereupon he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered. Dear Brother, if you are minded to travel you may, but as for me, I will ſtay in this Pallace, and ſpend my days in my Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Country. Then ſaid <hi>Andolocia,</hi> let us part the Iewels, give me my Portion and let me be gone: not ſo ſaid <hi>Ampedo,</hi> know you not that it was our fathers ſtrict Command when he dyed, that we ſhould not part them; no matter for that, ſaid <hi>Andolocia,</hi> now he is Dead, he will never repine at what we do; then ſaid <hi>Ampedo,</hi> take you your Hat and be packing; no, ſaid <hi>Andolocia,</hi> I will have the Purſe, if any: upon this, there aroſe a hot diſpute between them, till <hi>Andolocia</hi> ſaid, then if you needs will have Mony, fill two Coffers out of the Purſe, and take the Hat and the reſt of the Iewels, with free poſſeſſion of all the Houſes and Pallaces, and give me the Purſe only; and at ſix Years end, I will return and deliver it you again; to this <hi>Ampedo</hi> conſented, leſt in the heat of Quarrel, the ſecrets of the Purſe ſhould be revealed, and ſo the difference between them was ended,</p>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="chapter">
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:54800:36"/>
               <head>CHAP. XXIX How <hi>Andolocia</hi> went with his Purſe into the <hi>French</hi> Court, and what entertainment he foun.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>there.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>ANdolocia,</hi> having got the Purſe, departed joyfully, and after having paſſed through many Countrys, at laſt he came into <hi>France,</hi> when repairing to <hi>Paris</hi> the chief City, he went to view the ſplendor of the Kings Court: where attiring himſelf after the beſt manner, he accompanied himſelf with the Nobility and Gentry, ſpend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing even to admiration; for ſuch was his liberality, that he exceeded moſt of the Nobility; and kept ſuch ſtately entertainment, and ſuch coſtly Garbs, as the Country did afford: but long he had not ſtayed there, before Iuſts were ordeined, and a Challenge made by certain Noble Perſonages againſt any that durſt Encounter them: upon which <hi>Andolocia</hi> prepared for the Combat, and unhorſed three Earls, one after another: of which the King took great notice, and ordered that he ſhould be entertained in his Pallace; when night came, the Ladys and Gentlemen were diſpoſed to Dance; amongſt which, the King would have <hi>Andolocia</hi> make one, where he ſo well behaved him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, that all the Eyes of the Ladys were upon him; and from that time forth they highly eſteemed him, and he, by often converſing with them, at laſt fell deep in Love with one of them, who was a beautifull Lady, and Wife to a Courtier of <hi>Andolocia's</hi> acquaintance: and ſo paſſionate he was, that finding a fit opportunity he told her his deſire, ſaying, that if ſhe would conſent to lye with him but one night, he would give her a 1000 Crowns; but ſhe being a Virtuous Lady re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed his proffer, and acquainted her Husband what offer <hi>Andolocia</hi> had made: who conſidered what a great help a 1000 Crowns would be to him in his neceſſity, yet was very loath to be a Cuckold; ſo that caſting about, they at laſt agreed to get a Neighbour of theirs to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly her Room, and ſo to deceive him in his Expectation; this liked them both very well, whereupon, when <hi>Andolocia</hi> importun'd her a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, ſhe gave him hopes, telling him that ſuch an Evening her Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band would be abroad about earneſt buſineſs, and then if he would
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:54800:37"/> come and bring with him the Mony he ſhould be entertained to his wiſh. This rejoyced not <hi>Andolocia</hi> a little, who thought every hour a day till the happy Lover was come: now in the mean time, ſhe went to her Neighbour and told her, ſhe ſhould have a 100 Crowns if ſhe would but proſtitute her Body to a Gentleman in her ſtead, ſo that it might not be diſcerned; for, ſaid ſhe, I would willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly do it, but that my Husband ſo narrowly watches me that I have no opportunity; to this the Neighbour freely conſented, without any Scruple of Conſcience, as being uſed to the Trade, and ſo at the time appointed <hi>Andolocia</hi> came and brought the Mony, which the Lady took, then biding him ſit down, ſhe conveyed her Neighbour in at a back Door, and put her into her own Bed, and when it was dark, <hi>Andolocia,</hi> was by the Chamber-Maid whom he bribed with 20 Crowns, led to the Bed, and there pulling off his Cloaths in he went, and imbraced the Gentlewoman with abundance of kindneſs, ſporting it by times till it was almoſt day; when as his Bed-fellow would have riſen, but he would not ſuffer her: ſo that ſhe knowing when light appeared, ſhe ſhould be diſcovered, for fear freely confeſſed the whole matter: which greatly grieved him that he had been ſo deceived, for inſtead of a beautiful Gentlewoman whom he thought he had in Bed with him, he had imbraced a common Strumpet; yet diſſembling the matter as well as he could, gave the Baggage a 100 Crowns, telling her what he had given the Gentlewoman before; and ordered her as ſoon as he was departed the City, to ſue for them, ſeeing the Gentlewoman had not performed her promiſe; which ſhe being arm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with impudence did accordingly, and put the Lady to great ſhame and diſgrace</p>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXX.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How <hi>Andolocia</hi> went to the King of <hi>Spain's</hi> Court, and of the noble entertainment he received there, and what Atchieve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments he made.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>ANdolocia</hi> having had this Female cheat put upon him, reſolved to ſtay no longer in the <hi>French</hi> Court, leſt it ſhould be noiſed
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:54800:37"/> abroad to his diſgrace: but immediately taking Horſe, he rode with his Servants to <hi>Navar,</hi> from thence to <hi>Aragon,</hi> and ſo to the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh</hi> Court, which in thoſe days greatly flouriſhed, where, for the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter entertainment, he put himſelf into a <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Garb, for ſuch is the humour of that Nation; that they will, by their good wills, ſort themſelves with none but ſuch as comply with their faſhion. At that time there were Wars with <hi>Portugal,</hi> ſo that <hi>Andolocia</hi> raiſing a 100 men payed them himſelf, and rid at the head of them in the King's Service; where by his Valour and undaunted Courage, he got himſelf great Praiſe, inſomuch that the King taking notice of it, not only Knighted him, but likewiſe beſtowed many rich preſents on him, and proferred to Marry him to the Daughter of an antient Earl; with whom after the Father's Deceaſe, he ſhould have the Earldom: but <hi>Andolocia</hi> humbly thanked his Majeſty, ſaying, that he was not diſpoſed to Marry, for that he was reſolved to ſee many Countrys.</p>
               <p>Within a while after the Wars ceaſing, <hi>Andolocia</hi> diſmiſſed his Souldiers, and took leave of the King, who was very loath to part with him; yet, <hi>Andolocia</hi> urging him, he bid him farewell, and when ever he came into <hi>Spain</hi> again, to make uſe of his Court, as freely as if it were his own: after he had left the King, he took Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and ſailed for <hi>England,</hi> when coming up the River of <hi>Thames,</hi> he landed at the <hi>Tower</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> and much admired the ſtrong and ſtately Building; when coming to the Court, and having ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken a view of the ſame, he ſearched for a ſtately Houſe as near to it as poſſible: which he having found, furniſhed it after the beſt man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and retained many Men and Maid-ſervants, keeping a very plentiful Table, inſomuch that a great many of the Courtiers re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorted dayly thither, and were by him feaſted; of which the King hearing, he ſent for him, and asked him what he was, who according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly told him; then ſaid the King, will you be content to have a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand under me in the Wars againſt the <hi>Scots?</hi> Yes, with a very good will ſaid <hi>Andolocia,</hi> and will raiſe and maintain a hundred men at my proper coſt and charges: at this the King was greatly pleaſed, and made him a Captain, ſo that going againſt the Enemy, he fought ſo manfully that he broke their Ranks, and greatly diſordered
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:54800:38"/> them, inſomuch that freſh forces coming on, they ſoon put them to the rout, and although many did bravely that day, yet <hi>Andolocia</hi> did beſt, which yet the more indear'd the King to him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXXI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How <hi>Andolocia</hi> being at Dinner with the King, fell in Love with a <hi>Agrypina</hi> the Princeſs, and what happened after.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>ANdolocia</hi> was no ſooner returned from the Wars, but the King ſent his Stewerd to invite him to Dinner, as likewiſe ſeveral of the chief Commanders were likewiſe preſent, many Ladys and Gentlewomen, and amongſt the reſt, the Princeſs of <hi>Agrypina,</hi> who, for beauty, ſurpaſſed all her Sex: on her <hi>Andolocia</hi> fixing his Eyes, ſo ſurfrited on her beauty, that he could never eat nor drink to any purpoſe, but ſtill kept his Eyes fixed on her: and wiſhed that he was a Prince for her ſake, though, ſaid he, I am as well able to keep her, as ever a Prince in Chriſtendom; yet, I not being of Royal Blood, it will be but in vain for me to flatter my ſelf into a belief, that ſhe will condeſcend to my requeſt, ſhould I ask her yet; 'tis but trying: and from the time forth, <hi>Andolocia</hi> attired himſelf in Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and Gold, and would ever be the formoſt in Tilts and Iuſts that were to be before the King, Queen, and Princes, where he won great Applauſe; after which taking his opportunity, he invited the Queen and her Daughter to Dinner, and ſo ſplendidly entertained them, that they had not beheld the like in the King's <hi>Pallace;</hi> and at their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture, gave each of them a Rich Iewel, which they very readily ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted. At <hi>Andolocia</hi>'s next coming to Court the King met him, and told him that he heard how he had entertained the Queen and Princeſs to their content, ſaying, if he had but known of his Feaſt, he would have been there in Perſon; whereupon <hi>Andolocia</hi> excuſed himſelf, ſaying, he durſt not preſume ſo high, as to invite His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty; but that if he would ſo far Honour him with his Preſence, he would be infinitely obliged to him for ſo great an Honour: to this the King conſented, and appointed the next day to come, whereupon
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:54800:38"/> 
                  <hi>Andolocia</hi> provided a more coſtly entertainment than before: inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that the King marveled how he could live at that rate: ſeveral Fires he made of <hi>Ceder</hi> and Spices, which caſt a fragrant ſmell, ſo that the King and ſeveral of his Nobles ſat down, and were exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing merry; continuing there till Evening, and then departed: at whoſe departure, <hi>Andolocia</hi> gave mony amongſt the Guards, and humbly thanked the King for the Honour he had done him.</p>
               <p>When the King came to the Court, he told the Queen and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs how bravely he had been entertained; and that he did not a little wonder how <hi>Andolocia,</hi> having neither Lands nor Subjects, to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance, could ſpend ſo liberally; therefore he ſaid, he believed he muſt be ſome Prieſt in diſguiſe: truly, ſaid the Queen, I can but wonder as well as you! and have had a longing mind to know how he comes by ſo much mony, and of late I have bethought my ſelf of the means: he has, for ſome time paſt, he profeſſed great Love to our Daughter, the which by many Simptomes I well perceive is unfeigned; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I intend to Advertiſe her of my Purpoſe, and if ſhe ſhew him but a little kindneſs, I know he will not deny her any thing; this well pleaſed the King, and thereupon he ordered <hi>Aggrypina</hi> to ſearch out the matter, who promiſed to uſe her utmoſt diligence therein.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXXII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How the Princeſs came to know the ſecret of the Purſe, and how ſhe deceived <hi>Andolocia</hi> of the ſame.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>THe next Morning <hi>Andolocia</hi> coming to the Court, was ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted into <hi>Agrypina's</hi> Chamber, a favour that he never be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore enjoyed; at which he exceedingly rejoyced, thinking with himſelf that this was a happy opportunity, and proſperous; he had not long been there before the Princeſs came, and with a merry Countenance, wiſhed him a good Morning; at which he humbly thanked her Grace, and then ſhe cauſed him to ſit down by her, and fell to diſcourſe about divers Affairs: as of his Travels, Birth, and Parentage, ſo that in ſuch like diſcourſes, they ſpent much time; then began <hi>Andolocia</hi>
                  <pb n="72" facs="tcp:54800:39"/> to expreſs the paſſion he had for her, and that how for her ſake, he would adventure any hazard. Alas! ſaid ſhe, I am not at my own diſpoſe, for if I were, your Eſtate would ſoon decreaſe at the rate you live, and then I ſhould come to poverty; fear not that my Love, and deareſt part of Life, my Eſtate can never grow leſs then it is, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I ſhould ſpend a Million a week: then belike ſaid <hi>Aggrypina,</hi> your Father is ſome Puiſſant Prince: not ſo, ſaid <hi>Andolocia,</hi> my Father is Dead, nor was he, neither am I, a Prince; his Riches and mine were equal, and though we both have ſpent to exceſs, yet had we never the leſs.</p>
               <p>This made <hi>Aggrypina</hi> wonder, and therefore ſhe was the more deſirous to know whence this infinite Treaſure ſhould flow, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to ſhew better Countenance than ever, ſaying, you have often told me you loved me <hi>Andolocia;</hi> and in that, ſaid he, I have not ſaid amiſs; for I proteſt by all that's ſacred, I admire and adore you a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all Women kind, eſteeming you, as indeed you are, the faireſt of your Sex: many Ladys have I ſeen in Forraign Courts, but your bright perfections as far excells them all, as the Sun does the paler Luſtre of the Moon; therefore vouchſafe dear Lady to cure the Wounds you have made, and pardon my boldneſs.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>woodcut of a woman standing, Andolocia and the King sitting at a table</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>repetitive woodcut of multiple trees</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>She was no ſooner come but they demanded how ſhe ſped, to which ſhe anſwered, ſhe had ſped as ſhe wiſhed, for here ſays ſhe is the Gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Purſe; and with that, putting her hand into it, ſhe pulled out ſeveral handfuls of Gold, at which the King and Queen greatly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyced: then the King demanded her to give it into his keeping, but the Queen ſaid, ſince ſhe had ventured for it, it was but Reaſon ſhe ſhould keep it.</p>
               <p>Now whilſt this diſcourſe held, <hi>Andolocia</hi> awoke, and ſtarting up as one amazed, found that he had ſlept in the Chair all night, which did not a little perplex him; when in the midſt of his trouble, in came the Old Woman, of whom he demanded where <hi>Aggrypina</hi> was? ſhe told him that ſhe having layn alone all night in expectation of his waking and coming to bed to her, ſhe was now riſen, being ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry much grieved that he ſhould ſo diſappoint her. And farther ſhe told him, that although they jogged him, and uſed many endeavours, they could not wake him; then concluded <hi>Andolocia,</hi> it was done by the Inchantment of ſome that envyed his happineſs, and thereupon departed penſive to his Houſe, as having loſt ſo happy an opportunity; that he was out of all hopes of regaining ſuch another, but little dreamt his Purſe was gone.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="33" type="chapter">
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:54800:40"/>
               <head>CHAP. XXXIII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How the King ſent to <hi>Andolocia</hi> to prepare a Dinner for him, and how when he found his Purſe was loſt, he left his Houſe in great heavyneſs, and departed for <hi>Cyprus.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>NOw the King being deſirous to try how <hi>Andolocia</hi> would be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>have himſelf after the loſs of his Purſe, ſent his Steward to him to acquaint him, that by reaſon a ſtranger was come to Court, he purpoſed to bring him to his Houſe, and therefore willed him to provide accordingly, which <hi>Andolocia</hi> promiſed, as not yet having eſſayed his Purſe. After the Meſſenger was gone, he called his Steward, and bid him provide for the King's entertainment, ſuch things as he thought moſt fit; to which he replyed, his mony was ſpent in the late coſtly Banquets, and to furniſh a new one he muſt have more mony; with that <hi>Andolocia</hi> put his hand into his Purſe as formerly, but to his great amazement found nothing in it; then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan he to turn it and look upon it, but found it was not the ſame: then he waxed exceeding ſorrowful, and much repented him of his folly, that, contrary to his Fathers Command, he had declared the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets of his Purſe: as likewiſe, how he had been deceived by a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man not long before, which might have been a fair warning to him how he again truſted any of that treacherous Sex; and in utter diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair ever to gain it by fair means, he called all his Servants about him, telling them that he had heard of the Death of his Brother in <hi>Cyprus,</hi> and muſt inſtantly depart thither to take Poſſeſſion of his Land, and therefore willed them to take what wages was due: beſides their Horſes and the furniture of the Houſe he would freely beſtow upon them, and then leave them to ſhift for themſelves, for that it would be too great a trouble to carry Servants over the Sea.</p>
               <p>At this ſuddain news they were all diſmayed, telling him that they would venture their Lives and Fortunes with him wherever he went: but he told them it muſt not be, but that if ever he returned to <hi>England,</hi> he would find them out, and entertain them as former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; and ſo taking his leave of them, he rid to the Sea, all alone, and there taking Ship departed for <hi>Cyprus.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="34" type="chapter">
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:54800:41"/>
               <head>CHAP. XXXIIII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How <hi>Andolocia</hi> arrived at <hi>Cyprus,</hi> and declared to <hi>Ampedo,</hi> all that had happened.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>ANdolocia</hi> ſanding in the Iſle of <hi>Cyprus,</hi> haſted to <hi>Famogoſta</hi> and entring the Pallace, where he meeting his Brother, they kindly embraced, and asked of each others Welfare; for now <hi>Ampe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do</hi> thought to have his turn of the Purſe: but when he beheld his Brother penſive and ſad, he much doubted the event, and there upon began to ask him what was become of his men? nay, ſays he, as for them I take no farther care, but am glad my ſelf is returned with Life. Then <hi>Ampedo</hi> began to ask him about the Purſe, who an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered in a mournful tone, that by diſobliging his Fathers Command, he had loſt it; how! ſaid <hi>Ampedo,</hi> by fraud or force? nay, ſaid he, by fraud; for falling in Love with a fair Lady, her beauty ſo far bewitched me, that at her intreaty I told her the ſecret virtue of it; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch that when I was aſleep, ſhe got it from my Girdle, and pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced a falſe one in the Room of it. This it is, ſaid <hi>Ampedo,</hi> to be diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient, had it not been better for you to have ſtayed at home, without running any hazard, then thus to looſe the beſt Treaſure the World can afford? now, if we come to poverty, ſhall we be the laughing ſtock and ſcorn of all that have formerly known our manner of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving. Good Brother, ſaid <hi>Andolocia,</hi> do not aggravate my ſorrow, for I grieve ſufficiently, and repent me of my folly; inſomuch that I fear it will caſt me into ſome dangerous ſickneſs, of which I ſhall dye: when <hi>Ampedo</hi> heard him ſay ſo, he began to leave off chiding, and ſtrove to comfort him, ſaying, well! ſince it is loſt, let it go, I have yet 3000 Duckets left, beſides the Wiſhing Hat, for which I doubt not to get a great ſumm of mony, when ſome Puiſſant Prince ſhall know the vertue of it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="35" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXXV.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How <hi>Andolocia</hi> deceived his Brother, and got his Wiſhing Hat, with which he came into <hi>England,</hi> and carried away <hi>Aggrypina</hi> and the Purſe, into a deſart place, and what there befel.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>NOw when <hi>Andolocia</hi> had continued a while with his Brother, he one day told him, that if he would lend him his Wiſhing
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:54800:41"/> Hat, he did not yet doubt to recover the Purſe: but <hi>Ampedo</hi> would by no means conſent thereto, ſaying, that he was wiſer than ſo, and that the beſt way was to ſit down w th the firſt loſs; for, ſaid he, I doubt not but to get 10000 Duckets for the Hat when our mony is ſpent: ſo that when <hi>Andolocia</hi> perceived he would not part with it for an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Voyage, he let him alone a good while, and then ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king his opportunity when his men were gon a Hunting, he deſired him to let him have the Hat only to get amongſt them, that he might ſee the ſport: to this <hi>Ampedo</hi> conſented, but <hi>Andolocia</hi> had no ſooner put it on, but he wiſhed himſelf at <hi>Venice,</hi> and was inſtantly conveyed there through the Ayr: where he enquired for ſeveral <hi>Jews</hi> who were wont to trade in Rich Iewels, and deſired that he might ſee their Iewels, the which they conſented to, in hopes of a Chapman; but <hi>Andolocia</hi> had no ſooner got them in his hands, but he wiſhed himſelf in <hi>England,</hi> and was ſuddenly carryed thither, the <hi>Jews</hi> imagining him to be no other than the Devil; and bleſſed themſelves that they did not take any of his mony.</p>
               <p>When he came into <hi>England,</hi> he diſguiſed himſelf in an <hi>Italian</hi> habit, and getting on a long Gown, went to the Court, and there pretending himſelf to be a Merchant, he inſinuated into the Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of <hi>Aggrypina's</hi> Gentlewomen, by giving them ſmall preſents, that ſo they ſhould perſwade the Princeſs to buy his Iewels, which were very rich; with which they ſoon acquainted her, and willed him to ſpread them abroad as ſhe paſſed by, which he accordingly did, and ſhe caſting her Eyes upon them, asked if he would ſell any of them? yes, and if it ſhall pleaſe your Highneſs, I am come from a far Country for that purpoſe; then ſhe choſe out ſeveral of the beſt, and asked him the Price, who told her ſhe ſhould have them for 6000 Crowns, whereupon ſhe bid him 3000 Crowns; but he immagin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that ſhe would bring out the Purſe, bargained with her for 4000 Crowns, and then ſhe ordering him to bring them into her Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, went to a Coffer, and taking thence the Purſe, tyed it faſt to her Girdle: which was what <hi>Andolocia</hi> looked for, who whilſt ſhe was telling out the Mony, claſped her faſt by the Arm, and throwing her upon his back, he wiſhed himſelf in a Solitary Deſart: and imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately they were both carryed out of ſight, to the great amazement of
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:54800:42"/> thoſe that beheld it, and were not let down till they came into <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> then <hi>Aggrypina</hi> being faint, <hi>Andolocia</hi> placed her under a Tree, on which were many Apples, exceeding fair to appearance: when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as ſhe made her requeſt to <hi>Andolocia,</hi> that if he had any pitty of a poor diſtreſſed Virgin, he would get her ſomething to quench her thirſt, or ſhe ſhould faint; with that he taking pitty of her, as loving her ſtill, although ſhe had ſo miſuſed him, he got up the tree, and through careleſneſs left the Hat upon her Head, and the Iewels in her lap, who whilſt he was plucking the Apples, ſaid, Woe is me! how came I hither into this forlorn and deſart place? O! how unlike is this to my Father's Country, I would to God I were in my Father's Palace again: the which when <hi>Andolocia</hi> heard, he haſted down the Tree to ſtay her flight, but ſhe was gone, paſt recovery, in a moment, with the Purſe, Hat, and Iewels, which vexed <hi>Andolocia</hi> worſe than before: whereupon he began to Curſe the Deſtinies, and the Hour wherein he was borne, ſaying, that now he was quite undone, and his loſs unreparable! When he had bewailed his misfortune a good while, he being faint and dry eat the Apples, upon which he felt a ſuddain pain in his Head, which made him ſuppoſe they were infecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous; but it continued not long, before a large pair of Goats Horns ſprung up, at which he was ſore affrighted, and would have fled from
<figure>
                     <figDesc>repetitive woodcut of single tree</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>woodcut of two men standing and one flying</figDesc>
                  </figure> him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t had it been poſſible; and began more than before to exclaim againſt his hard Fate, ſaying, that now ſuch a misfortune was befel
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:54800:42"/> him, as would exclude him from the Honour and Society of men; then began he to Curſe the time when he firſt came into <hi>England;</hi> and wiſhed that he had died in the Womb, or as ſoon as ever he beheld the light: Curſing and Railing againſt the Inchanting beauty of <hi>Aggrypina,</hi> which had wrought him all this diſgrace, and miſery; vowing, if poſſible, to be revenged; and was grown ſo deſperate, that he reſolved to ſell his Soul to the Devil, rather then ſhe ſhould go un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puniſhed. And in this mad mode he ranged the Forreſt, for two days ſpace, without meeting either Man or Beaſt: till at laſt he came to a Cave under a ſpreading Oak, wherein lived an aged Hermet, who not only calmed his deſperate reſolves, but likewiſe cured him of his Horns, as ſhall in the next Chapter he ſhown at large.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="36" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXXVI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How <hi>Andolocia,</hi> by the advice of an Hermet, was eaſed of his Horns, and how he came into <hi>England,</hi> and grafted a pair of Goats Horns upon the Head of <hi>Aggrypina.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>woodcut of a man unlocking a door with four men standing behind him; repeated from p. 32</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>repetitive woodcut of multiple trees</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>Now after they had held a long diſcourſe about the buſineſs of the World, the Hermit bid <hi>Andolocia</hi> be mindful of the future ſtate of his precious and immortal Soul: and ſo guiding him to the next Town, he diſmiſſed him with his Bleſſing; and <hi>Andolocia</hi> on the other hand, returned him a thouſand Thanks. Then went <hi>Ando<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locia</hi> to the next Inn and called for Meat and Drink, afterwards he departed thence toward the Sea-ſide, ſtudying all the way how he might be revenged on <hi>Agrippina;</hi> and having ſome of the Hornify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Apples in his Pocket, as likewiſe four of the contrary quality, which the Hermit had given him, he reſolved to go for <hi>London,</hi> and if poſſible, to graft a pair of Horns upon the head of <hi>Agrippina,</hi> by which means he doubted not to recover his Hat and Purſe; in order
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:54800:43"/> to which, he agreed with the Maſter of the Veſſel to carry him into <hi>England;</hi> when coming to <hi>London,</hi> he diſguiſed himſelf, and ſo went to the Court, and there putting his Apples in a Box, he ſet them forth juſt as the Princeſs was coming by: and when any one asked him what Fruit they were, he told them they were brought from <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and that they grew in the Holy Garden; which made ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny inquire the price, but he held them ſo dear that none would buy; it not being his intent that any ſhould experiment the ſecret; he had not long continued before <hi>Agrippina</hi> came by, and caſting her eyes upon them, ſhe not being accuſtomed to ſee ſuch kind of Fruit, demanded what they were? then her Gentlewoman told her; whereupon ſhe made towards <hi>Andolocia,</hi> and takeing one up in her hand, asked the price? which he told her was 3 Crowns the leaſt; for, ſays he, I have not above Twenty of them, and it has coſt me a twelve-months Travel to fetch them; ſome, 'tis true, I diſpos'd of in the Court of <hi>France,</hi> where they are highly approved for their vertue. Well, and what vertue, ſaid the Princeſs, do they contain? Such, ſaid <hi>Ando<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locia,</hi> that if you were old they would reſtore both Youth and Beauty; they are not only pleaſant to taſte, but have ſuch a miraculous ſecret, that they once being eaten, preſerve health for 7 Years after; but how many, ſaid <hi>Agrippina?</hi> only Two, ſaid <hi>Andolocia.</hi> Vpon this, the Princeſs, who was ſometimes troubled with Fits, bought Two of them, but would give him no more than two Crowns a piece and putting them in her Handkerchief, departed; which did not make <hi>Andolocia</hi> a little rejoyce; ſo ſtaying about the Court, he perceived by the melancholly temper of her waiting-Gentlewoman that the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject had taken effect; for ſo it was, that when the Princeſs came into her Chamber, ſhe eat one of the Apples, and finding it had a luſcious taſte, eat, in a while afterwards, another; then lying down to ſleep, as was her uſual cuſtome, ſhe found her ſelf ſomewhat indiſpoſed, but yet ſlept for half an hour; during which ſpace, ſhe Dreamed that a great He-Goat came running at her, and butted with his Horns; whereupon ſhe ſtriving to flye, found her ſelf turned into a Goat alſo; at which being much affrighted, ſhe awoke, when ſtarting up, ſhe felt a more then uſual weight upon her head; when looking in the Glaſs, ſhe eſpyed a great pair of Horns fixed upon her head, whereat
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:54800:44"/> ſhe ſhrieked out, ſo that her Gentlewomen came running, and when they beheld her, they ſhrieked alſo; but the old Matron who was her Tutor, being wiſer then the reſt, bid them keep ſilence; for, ſaid ſhe, if this be noiſed abroad, the greateſt Beauty upon Earth will looſe her credit amongſt Men; but the beſt way will be to procure ſuch a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Phyſitians as may take them away: then asked ſhe of <hi>Agrippi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> which way ſhe deemed that they happened? to which <hi>Agrippina</hi> replyed, I know not, unleſs it be ſome immediate judgement ſhewed upon me for my too great opinion of my beauty, or the effects of the ſtrange Fruit I bought of the Merchant; but however they came, I pray you ſeek ſome means by which I may be rid of them, whatever it coſt me, before it comes to be blazed about in the World; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the old Woman went to all the noted Phyſitians, and acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them what had happened to a fair young Gentlewoman, but told them not her name; then many of them deſired to ſee her, but ſhe told them that might not be, unleſs unſight or unſeen they would promiſe and oblige themſelves in an obligation of 2000 Crowns if they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed it not; but they looking upon it as a ſtrange and unheard of matter, would not undertake it upon ſuch conditions; ſo that the old Matron was returning home ſad and heavy that ſhe had not ſped: when <hi>Andolocia</hi> who had watched her all the while, meeting her at a turning, being now in the habit of a Doctor with great falſe, Whisk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and other diſguiſes, drew near and ſaluted her, ſaying, What makes you ſo ſad, is not ſome one of your friends well? for ſo I do gueſs, becauſe I ſee you come out of ſuch a Doctor's houſe: Truely, ſaid ſhe, there is ſomething more than ordinary that makes me thus: then ſaid <hi>Andolocia,</hi> be not afraid to diſcover it, for by my skill and God's bleſſing, I have done miraculous Cures, left off by other Phyſitians.</p>
               <p>When the Matron heard him ſay ſo, ſhe greatly rejoyced, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared to him in all points what had happened, which was to him no news; and deſired him to ſtay till ſhe went and acquainted the young Gentlewoman with it, and ſhe would return to him within an hour: the which he promiſed to do; ſo that when the Old Gentlewoman re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned, ſhe enjoyned him to keep ſecreſie, and to promiſe the payment of 2000 Crowns if he did not perform the Cure, and then ſhe led him up a back way into <hi>Agrippina's</hi> Chamber.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="chapter">
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:54800:44"/>
               <head>CHAP. XXVII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How <hi>Andolocia,</hi> by undertaking to Cure <hi>Agrippina</hi> of her Horns, firſt recovered his Wiſhing-Hat, and afterwards his Purſe, with what happened during the time.</p>
               </argument>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>repetitive woodcut of single tree</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>woodcut of Aggrypina in bed with horns, Andolocia bowing before her; Aggrypina and Andolocia running together</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>Then ſaid the King, I wiſh I had never perſwaded her to bereave <hi>Andolocia</hi> of his inchanted Purſe: for had he kept that ſtill, we had had our Daughter: for paſt doubt, he is a <hi>Negromancer</hi> himſelf, or deals with ſuch as are, and by that means has theſe two times con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyed her away: and I am verily perſwaded, that the Merchant and
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:54800:46"/> the Phyſitian were no other than <hi>Andolocia</hi> under diſguiſe; but I well truſt, that he is of ſo courteous a temper, that he will do our Daughter no harm: but when he hath obliged her to return him his Purſe, he will ſend her home again: for it is certain, that Purſe can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be quietly enjoyed by any but the true owner, which is <hi>Andolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia;</hi> therefore were my <hi>Aggrypina</hi> here, I did not care ſhe ſhould any more be troubled with it; but if I might get it, I would ſend it to <hi>Andolocia,</hi> and excuſe her taking it from him. After this, the Queen urged him to ſend forth meſſengers, not only into all parts of his own Dominions, but likewiſe into Forreign parts, which he commanded to be ſpeedily done, and ſo departed ſorrowfully to his Chamber: where I muſt leave him, and return into <hi>Scotland,</hi> to <hi>Andolocia</hi> and <hi>Aggrypina.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When <hi>Aggrypina</hi> was come to her ſelf, and able to ſpeak, ſhe fell upon her knees, and beſought <hi>Andolocia</hi> to have mercy upon her: for that ſhe confeſſed ſhe had greatly injured him, for which ſhe was heartily ſorry: and it was true, it lay in his power to revenge it, but that ſuch a revenge would ſtain his Glorious Deed in Arms, if once it came to light, as it was moſt likely it would; for, ſaid ſhe, Murther is not rarely concealed long, the guilty conſcience of the Murtherer being often conſtrained to diſcover it; but this did not abate <hi>Andolocia's</hi> anger, who fiercely replyed, well may you bluſh with ſhame and confuſion of face, ſince you have ſo treacherouſly dealt with one, who loved you beyond all earthly things; diſcovering to you that ſecret, which all the Racks and Tortures upon Earth, could never have obliged him to have done: tremble therefore at your guilt, for ſee revenge is written in my brow, and upon that, he layed his hand upon his Sword; which <hi>Aggrypina</hi> perceiving, that no other, but that he intended to diſpatch her, and therefore through fear and grief, ſhe fell into a ſwound, which moved <hi>Andolocia</hi> to pitty; ſo that he gently raiſed her from the ground, and ſhe recovering, began to beg him to pitty her, pitty you! ſaid <hi>Andolocia,</hi> what pitty can there remain in my breſt for ſuch an one who ſo treacherouſly and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratefully rewarded me for all the hazards that I underwent for your ſake? and know you ſhall ware the infamy on your front, as an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting Memento of your Infidelity. Then ſaid <hi>Aggrypina,</hi>
                  <pb n="87" facs="tcp:54800:46"/> I deſire you to place me in ſome Nunnery, thereby to keep me from the ſight of People, to which <hi>Andolocia</hi> conſented.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="38" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXXVIII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How <hi>Andolocia</hi> put <hi>Aggrypina</hi> in a Nunnery, and departed with his Hat and Purſe to <hi>Famogoſta.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>ANdolocia</hi> having found a Nunnery, knocked at the Door, and deſired to ſpeak with the <hi>Matron,</hi> who after ſome time, came and demadded his buſineſs? who told her, that he would gladly ſpeak with her in private, whereupon ſhe took him by the hand, and led him into the Lodg; where he told her, that a ſtrange accident had hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened to a Lady of great birth and beauty, which was, that ſhe had two Horns growing out of her head, upon that the <hi>Matron</hi> wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and was greatly deſirous to ſee her: whereupon he went and fetch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: <hi>Aggrypina</hi> (who waited for his return, not far thence:) when he brought her: the Abbeſs wondered yet more, but did not ſeem to take any notice of the Horns, for fear of diſpleaſing <hi>Aggrypina,</hi> but went to her and imbraced her, biding her heartily welcome: per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving her partly demean, and that ſhe had been exceedingly well bred: then did they demand of <hi>Andolocia</hi> 200 Crowns, which ſhe ſaid was the Cuſtom of the Houſe, when any Young Lady firſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered, and that afterwards they had ſervants aſſigned to attend them after the beſt manner: upon this <hi>Andolocia</hi> took out his Purſe, and gave her 300 Crowns, ſaying, there is one hundred more than you asked; therefore let the Lady be carefully looked to, which the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron</hi> promiſed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="39" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXXIX.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How <hi>Andolocia</hi> returned to his Brother <hi>Ampedo,</hi> with the Hat and Purſe: and how at the requeſt of the King of <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prus,</hi> he freed <hi>Aggrypina</hi> out of the Nunnery, and took a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way her Horns.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>ANdolocia</hi> being rid of <hi>Aggrypina,</hi> departed joyfully with his Purſe and Hat, and being out of ſight, he wiſhed himſelf in <hi>Flanders,</hi> whether he was conveyed in a trice; and there for ſome time ſolacing himſelf in pleaſure, he fell in love with an Earl's daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, to whom he imparted the ſecret of his Hat, which ſhe privily in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to ſteal from him by night: but he having notice of it from
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:54800:47"/> one of her Virgins; to whom ſhe had revealed it by reaſon of his often repeated liberalities towards her, he took the opportunity to prevent her by wiſhing himſelf in <hi>Cyprus,</hi> which he inſtantly accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed; where he no ſooner arrived, but he hired him ſervants, and bought both himſelf and them Horſes, and then in a moſt ſplendid manner rode to <hi>Famogoſta;</hi> the which when he approached, his Brother <hi>Ampedo</hi> eſpying him from the Batalments of his Palace, he did not a little rejoyce; and withal, called to his ſervants to make ready his Horſes, and ſo rode out to meet him; when they came near each other, both of them alighted and embraced each other, neither, for a while, being able to ſpeak, for joy: after which, <hi>Ampedo</hi> asked <hi>Andolocia</hi> how he had ſped, who with a chearful countenance replyed, that he had recovered his Purſe again, which did not a little rejoyce <hi>Ampedo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>After much diſcourſe relating to their Travels, they came to the Pallace, where <hi>Ampedo</hi> ordered a ſumptuous Feaſt to be prepared, to welcome his Brother, to which they invited ſeveral of their friends, to rejoyce with them, and continued in great merriment for two days; at the end of which, <hi>Andolocia</hi> offered his Brother the Purſe, but he refuſed it, ſaying, he had enough, and that it cauſed great perplexity to ſuch as kept it; and therefore he willed <hi>Andolocia</hi> ſtill to detain it, which did not at all diſpleaſe him; for although he offered it his Brother, yet he was in hopes that he would not accept of it. When he had Revelled in the Pallace for a while, he took leave of his Brother, and went to the King's Court, where he no ſooner arrived, but the King had notice thereof, and ſent one of his Chamberlains to bring him to his Preſence; where, when he was come, he made a low obeyſance, after which the King wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comed him, and asked him of his Travels, of which he gave a large account, relating to the cuſtoms and faſhions of the Countries through which he had paſſed: Then the King demanded of him, whether he had been in the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Court; to which he replyed, he had: And have you, ſaid the King, ſeen the Princeſs <hi>Agrypina?</hi> I have, ſaid <hi>Andolocia:</hi> But do you know whether ſhe be found or not, ſince the news I received that ſhe was carryed away by Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gromancy? for I have a great mind to lay down the ponderous
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:54800:47"/> waight of Government, if I could match my Son to that Princeſs: Truly, ſaid <hi>Andolocia,</hi> I muſt confeſs I know where ſhe is, and if your Majeſty will ſend an Ambaſſage with the Prince's Picture, I will ſo order it, that ſhe ſhall be at her fathers Court before the Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſador arrives. At this the King greatly rejoyced, and highly honoured <hi>Andolocia,</hi> promiſing all things ſhould be done according to his directions, and deſired him to make good his word without delay; upon which he took his leave of the King; and after having departed a mile from the Pallace, he put on his Wiſhing-Hat, and was immediately conveyed to the Nunnery, where knocking at the Gate, deſired to ſpeak with the Matron, who no ſooner came to him, but he ſhewed her that he was deſirous to ſpeak with <hi>Aggripi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na;</hi> whereupon ſhe cauſed her to be called, knowing him to be the perſon who had brought her thither: When <hi>Aggrypina,</hi> came, ſhe could not refrain from weeping; whereupon he taking her by the hand, led her into a private Chamber, and told her, that he had been ranging the world about, to find fit Medicines to cure her of her Horns; and demanded of her, that if ſhe were cured, whither ſhe would wiſh her ſelf to be? Why, ſaid ſhe, with my Father, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy my former Freedom in his Pallace: Then, ſaid he, be it accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to thy wiſh; and thereupon he gave her two Apples, which he had reſerved, the which ſhe had no ſooner eaten, but ſhe ſhed her Horns; then he called the Matron, and told her, that <hi>Aggrypina</hi> was a King's Daughter, and that e're long ſhe ſhould be Marryed to a beautiful young Prince, and that, he having cured her of her Horns, did now intend to take her with him. The Abbeſs or Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron perceiving the wonderful change, greatly rejoyced, and praiſed God that he had wrought ſuch a miraculous alteration: Then <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolocia</hi> giving the Matron 200 Crowns more, and to <hi>Aggrypi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na's</hi> waiting Maid, a hundred, he departed with <hi>Aggrypina;</hi> and when he was come into a Forreſt, he put on his Wiſhing-Hat, and taking her in his arms, wiſhed himſelf in <hi>London,</hi> where he imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately arrived; and there ſetting down the Princeſs <hi>Aggrypina,</hi> without any word ſpeaking, wiſhed himſelf as <hi>Famagoſta,</hi> and was there in a trice: Now <hi>Aggrypina</hi> perceiving that ſhe was at <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> enquired the way to her Father<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Pallace, where ſhe ſoon arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, by the directions of the Citizens.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="40" type="chapter">
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:54800:48"/>
               <head>CHAP. XL.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How <hi>Aggrypina</hi> came again to the King and Queen; and how an Ambaſſador came from <hi>Cyprus</hi> to demand her in Marriage; together with her Marriage to the King of <hi>Cyprus.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>AGgrypina</hi> no ſooner arrived at the Pallace, but ſhe was met by ſome of the Ladies that had formerly waited upon her, who could not ſpeak to her for joy, but immediately run to the King and Queen to inform them what they had ſeen; upon which the King ordered a hundred pieces of gold, to be given to the firſt bringer of the news, and immediately went to meet <hi>Aggrypina,</hi> greatly rejoycing that he had recovered her; upon which occaſion, he proclaimed a great Feaſt throughout all his dominions, which was kept with great rejoycing; in the mid'ſt of which, an Ambaſſador came from <hi>Cyprus,</hi> of which the King having notice, cauſed him to be nobly entertained, and the next day he was introduced to his Audience, he being attended by many Nobles of <hi>Cyprus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When he came into the King's preſence, he declared his Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy, and delived his Maſters Letters; ſhewing likewiſe, the young Princ's Picture, which greatly pleaſed the King and Queen; then was the Picture ordered to be carryed to <hi>Aggrypina;</hi> as likewiſe the Relation of what had paſſed; the which, when ſhe beheld, ſhe at firſt, with feigned Modeſty, diſapproved of; but caſting to mind what <hi>Andolocia</hi> had ſaid, ſhe conſented; then were the King's Ships made ready, and a great number of Noble Ladies appointed to carry her over; when taking leave of the King and Queen, ſhe departed, though not without ſome tears on either ſide; for that ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a proſperous Gale, within two months they Landed in that Iſland; whereof notice being had, the King, his Queen, and all the Nobles of that Kingdom, came to welcome her on ſhore, with all manner of Muſick, and what ever could he invented, to entertain one of ſuch Noble Birth; all the people rejoycing that they had ſo fair
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:54800:48"/> a Princeſs to be hereafter their Queen; then did <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> conduct her to the City of <hi>Meduſa,</hi> where the King's Pallace was; againſt whoſe coming, a ſtately Banquet was prepared; and the more to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light
<figure>
                     <figDesc>repetitive woodcut of single tree</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>woodcut of a feast and hunting</figDesc>
                  </figure> the company, a Conjuror cauſed a Tree to grown on the Table, and a Hunting to paſs along, for their Diveriſement. Likewiſe, <hi>Andolocia</hi> attended, but would by no means take any notice of <hi>Aggrypina,</hi> for ſo it was ſecretly agreed between them; but he ſpent ſo Royally, that all the Nobility envyed him, by reaſon he ecclipſed their Honours, in doing ſo far beyond their Abilities, by giving the Prince and Princeſs a Preſent of Iewels worth a hundred Crowns; as likewiſe ſending in ſuch ſtore of choice Vſands and Wine, that the King greatly maruelled.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="41" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XLI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How at the Sports and Paſtimes ordained to grace the Wedding, <hi>Andolocia</hi> won the praiſe; which cauſed ſome of the Nobility greatly to envy him.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>DVring the Feaſt the K. ordained ſeveral Sports, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nantenes, and fighting at Bor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ets; wherein <hi>Andolocia</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="92" facs="tcp:54800:49"/> prevailed, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> won the praiſe of all Ladies and Gentlewomen, and was by the Princeſs <hi>Aggrypina</hi> often Crowned with Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands; which raiſed the envy of many of the great ones againſt him, inſomuch that two Earls, <hi>viz.</hi> the Earl of <hi>Limoſe</hi> and <hi>Armandalia,</hi> ſecretly conſpired his death, becauſe he had obtained the Wreath ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral times, by putting them to the foile; ſo that they reſolved to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>y wait for him in a Wood, through which he was to paſs; for at th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t time he had not brought with him the Wiſhing-Hat, and reſolv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d to kill all his Men, and by putting him upon the Rack, oblige him to confeſs from whence he had ſuch ſtore of Treaſure: Whereupon the day before the Feaſt ended, they took their leave of the King, as if they intended to go a Hunting; and having got about 200 arm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d men, they placed themſelves behind certain Trees in the Wood, near to the way he was to paſs, and furiouſly ſetting upon him at una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wares, they killed all his Men, which were 6 in umber, and took him Priſoner, though not without loſs on their ſide, for <hi>Andolocia</hi> draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Sword, ſo laid about him, that he killed ten of their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and wounded the Earl of <hi>Limoſe.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="42" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XLII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How <hi>Andolocia</hi> was Impriſoned and Racked, and how <hi>Ampedo</hi> burned his Wiſhing-Hat, as imagining his Brother ſlain.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>WHen the Earls had taken <hi>Andolocia</hi> Priſoner, they carryed him to a Caſtle of theirs not far from thence, where they put him into a dark Priſon, and rode again to Court, carrying with them 4 fat Bucks, which they pretended to have taken by hunting. Soon after their arrival, news was brought of the death of <hi>Andolocia's</hi> men, and how that he was thought to be taken Priſoner, by reaſon his body was not found amongſt them, upon which, the King was exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing angry; and immediately ſent out Meſſengers into all parts of the Kingdom; to hear of him: As likewiſe <hi>Ampedo</hi> offered a 1000 Duckets to any that could diſcover where he was; but when no ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings could he had where he was, he ſuppoſed him dead, or in ſome diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:54800:49"/> priſon; for the ſake of his Purſe; and thereupon left he ſhould come to ſome ill end, by reaſon of his Hat, he caſt it into the fire, and there let it conſume to aſhes, and for grief, within a ſhort time after dyed. Now when the Earls had been at Court ſome time, the Earl of <hi>Limoſe</hi> went to ſee what was become of <hi>Andolocia,</hi> and at his arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val, found him in the priſon where he left him, and there began to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine him where he had ſo much money to ſpend at the rate he did? he told him, that if he would let him go to the Pallace at <hi>Famagoſta,</hi> he would ſhow him by what means he obtained his Riches; but he would not conſent to it, but cauſed him grievouſly to be Racked; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch that he was obliged to diſcover the ſecrets of his Purſe, and he delivered it to the Earl in hopes, by that means, to be ſet free; but he having proved it, left him in Priſon, and rode to his Companion, and ſhewed him all that had happenned; whereupon they, after ſome conteſt agreed to keep it monthly by turns; then the Earl of <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandolia</hi> ſaid, I hear that <hi>Andolocia</hi> is a Negromancer, and can flie in the ayr: therefore we cannot be ſafe till he is diſpatched out of the way, to which they both agreed, and the Earl of <hi>Armandolia</hi> rode to the priſon, and offered the Keeper 200 Crowns to ſtrangle <hi>Andolocia,</hi> but he refuſed it, ſaying, he was a juſt and honeſt man: whereupon the Earl went in himſelf, and after having asked whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>her he had any more Purſes of the ſame ſort, and he affirming he had none, the Earl with his Girdle, ſtrangled him, as he ſat faſt in a large pair of Stocks, and ſo returned to the Earl of <hi>Limoſe,</hi> to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint him with what he had done.</p>
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:54800:50"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>woodcut of the murder of Andolocia and the murderers' execution on the breaking wheel</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>repetitive woodcut of multiple trees</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="42" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XLII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How the Murder of <hi>Andolocia</hi> was diſcovered by the two Earls falling out about the Purſe, and how they were put to death for the ſame.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>ANdolocia</hi> and <hi>Ampedo</hi> being dead, the Purſe loſt all its vertue, and would yield no more Money than any common Purſe; ſo that it falling to the Earl of <hi>Armandalia</hi>'s turn, he taxed the Earl of <hi>Limoſe</hi> as a Cheat, ſaying, he had changed it; ſo that there happened a diſpute between them; whereupon they drew their Swords and wounded each other; when as the people coming in to part them, the Earl of <hi>Limoſe</hi> ſaid; Ah Villain! then wouldeſt have Murthered me as thou didſt <hi>Andolocia</hi> for his Purſe; which words being told to the King, he ſuſpected them to be the Murther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers: Whereupon he commanded they ſhould be Apprehended and Racked; during which, they freely confeſſed all that had paſſed, and were Condemned to be broken upon the Wheel, their Chattels and Goods to be ſpotted, and ſo many as were conſenting or privy to the Murther, to be Hanged; which Sentance was accordingly put in Execution: After which, by reaſon <hi>Andolocia</hi> and <hi>Ampedo</hi> had left none to poſſeſs their Pallace at <hi>Famagoſta,</hi> the King took poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thereof, and found in it infinite Wealth, placing the Prince and Princeſs therein, who lived there in great Splendor, till the King's Death, and then took upon them the Rule of the whole Kingdom.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:54800:50"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
